<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scripture-warrant sufficient proof for infant-baptism: being a reply to Mr. Grantham's Presumption no proof Wherein his pretended answer to two questions propounded to the Anabaptists by G.F. is examined, and found to be no answer. With a brief discourse upon infant-regeneration, denyed by Anabaptists. Baptism without dipping valid. By Giles Firmin.</title>
            <author>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41332</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833808</idno>
  <idno type="VID">38286</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240915042</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F963A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222661</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833808</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99833808e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38286)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2207:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scripture-warrant sufficient proof for infant-baptism: being a reply to Mr. Grantham's Presumption no proof Wherein his pretended answer to two questions propounded to the Anabaptists by G.F. is examined, and found to be no answer. With a brief discourse upon infant-regeneration, denyed by Anabaptists. Baptism without dipping valid. By Giles Firmin.</title>
                  <author>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst at the Bible and Three Crowns at the lower end of Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In response to Grantham, Thomas.  Presumption no proof, or, Mr. Petto's arguments for infant-baptism considered and answered.</note>
                  <note>Copy tightly bound; with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692. --  Presumption no proof, or, Mr. Petto's arguments for infant-baptism considered and answered --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:1"/>
            <p>Scripture - Warrant SUFFICIENT PROOF FOR INFANT-BAPTISM: BEING A REPLY to Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi>'s <hi>Presumption no Proof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein his pretended Answer to Two Questions propounded to the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> by <hi>G. F.</hi> is Examined, and found to be no Answer.</p>
            <p>With a brief DISCOURSE upon INFANT-REGENERATION, Denyed by <hi>Anabaptists.</hi> BAPTISM without <hi>Dipping</hi> Valid.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GILES FIRMIN.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>That which is born of the Flesh, is Flesh. <bibl>
                  <hi>John 3.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Omnes enim venit per semetipsum salvare: omnes inquam qui per eum renascuntur in Deum, Infantes, &amp; Parvulos, &amp; Pueros, &amp; Juvenes &amp; Seniores. Ideò per omnem venit aetatem; &amp; Infantibus Infaus factus sanctificans Infantes: in parvulis parvulus, sanctificans hanc ipsam habentes aetatem,</hi> &amp;c. <bibl>Irenaeus advers. Haeres. <hi>l. 2. c. 39.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapside,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Did not know that the Question about the Conveniency or Inconveniency of Dissenters writing against Dissenters in this juncture of time, had been discussed by our Brethren; till having drawn up a few Arguments against Positions which some Anabaptists, coming down from <hi>London</hi> into these parts, had asserted, I sent them up to have them published: but Mr. <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> my worthy Friend (whom for his great pains in promoting <hi>Unity</hi> among Dissenters, I shall ever Honour) wrote me word, the Brethren there, had concluded, this was not a convenient time for Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters to write against Dissenters. I submitted to their judgment, and recalled my Copy.</p>
            <p>When I had done this, word was brought me from a young furious Zealot against Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, (calling it an <hi>Antichristian Cheat,)</hi> that there was an Answer printing to my two Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which I had propounded to the Anabaptists
<pb facs="tcp:38286:3"/>four years past; which proved true: for he sends me the Book, and gets the Books to be sold in our Town. So that now I hope my Brethren can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blame me, that I endeavour to vindicate the Truth of God, and defend my self.</p>
            <p>Before the Book was sent me, this young Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, tells in this, and other Towns, what this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Name was, what a great Writer he was, and that against Learned men, [that now I must expect a formidable Adversary to encounter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,] and gave this description of him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> is a person descended from a worshipfull Family, but in the time of the Civil Wars his Parents suffered much loss for the King. Being brought low, his Father puts out this his Son to a Taylour; and observing his Son inclining to <hi>Fanaticism</hi> (as some call it) he chose such a Master for him, as he thought would stifle those Principles: but his Son con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues sober, and helps to Reform those who wrought with him. His Apprentiship being out, he gave himself to study, and becomes a great Proficient in Learning: Disputed with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Bishop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> before he was Bishop, at which Disputation, several Priests were got behind the Hangings; with other Circumstances he mentioned, but the issue was, he worsted the Doctor so, that he quitted the room.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:3"/>
            <p>If there be any Errour in this, let not Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> blame me: for it came from one that is an Admirer of him. That he was a <hi>Taylour,</hi> I do not look at this, as being any real dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to him; it hath been the Case of others, that have descended from as good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies as his: But if Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> will be dealing in Polemical Divinity, and there scoffe at his Opponent, use provoking terms, write in some places absurdly, (as he doth against me) he must expect to hear of it sometimes.</p>
            <p>What the two Questions are I gave then to answer, the Reader will find them repeated in the following Discourse. I stated the Question firstly, with respect to the <hi>Jews,</hi> requiring him that answers, to set down the Scriptures, upon which he grounded his answer for the <hi>Negative,</hi> but he hath not named so much as One.</p>
            <p>I will give him for the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> these, <hi>first,</hi> for the <hi>Jews: Acts 2.39. Acts 3.25. Rom. 11.15, 16, 28, 29.</hi> [Of the two last I make use.] I need not mention any for the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> yet I will give him these. <hi>Ephes. 2.12.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.</hi> compared. <hi>1 Cor. 7.14. Gal. 3.14.</hi> By these I will defend my Question, yet he calls it an <hi>unlearned Question.</hi> What, when I have Scripture-grounds for it, and he cannot produce one for the contrary?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:4"/>
            <p>As for that Experience which I have given of the benefit of Improving <hi>Abrahams and our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptismal-Covenant,</hi> in my former little Treatise, which Learned and Godly Divines, say, cannot be without Grace, (and I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all the Learned and godly Divines in <hi>England,</hi> or elsewhere, that have experience of Gods work on their own hears,) this Mr. <hi>Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> scoffs at. I shall meet with him in his place.</p>
            <p>This onely I will say as to his Book: If my two Questions meet with no Better Answer than Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> hath given, I will go on to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the Infants of Believing Parents, without the Least Scruple.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>6 Jan. 87.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The Servant to the Seed of Believers,</hi> Giles Firmin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AFter I had finished my Copy, there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Book of Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi>'s sent to me: The title, <hi>Hear the Church.</hi> Where he hath several things, new fancies, to take with them who have a mind to Admire him. He talks of Church-Officers which he calls <hi>Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> All Gospel Preachers I hope are <hi>Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> in one sense: If orderly called, they are all <hi>sent. Rom. 10.15.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, there are <hi>Messengers,</hi> properly so call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and have known the practice about Fifty years since: but for <hi>Messengers</hi> in his sense, they are but his new invented Officers. I would have spoken to his Text in <hi>Revel. 2. Angels,</hi> but 'tis not worth the while; the man mistakes the Texts much, to make them serve his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>He tells his <hi>Brethren</hi> (as he calls them) p. <hi>41. Our Learned Adversaries, are wont to amuse weak Christians, by telling them they know not the Originals;</hi> there he gives them help, by telling them <hi>how vain and pernicious this talk is about the Originals.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:5"/>
            <p>If that be <hi>Vain and Pernicious,</hi> I am sure what he writes about the Hebrew and the Greek, is so <hi>Vain and Ridiculous,</hi> that I would not foul Paper to give him an Answer to it.</p>
            <p>But <hi>p. 43.</hi> there is something requires an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer: There he falls upon Papists and most Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, <hi>Who while they seem to admire Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils and Fathers, regard not the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the best Councils and Fathers in</hi> Act. <hi>15. but without all Conscience of these De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, seed upon blood: On the other side, how rigidly do they impose the Decrees of the Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>in the Case of</hi> Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation, <hi>though never heard of before it was there invented,</hi> &amp;c. Let the Papists bear their shame for their Persecution.</p>
            <p>For eating of Blood (in that manner we eat it) a few words. Considering, <hi>First,</hi> That the not eating of Blood was one of the seven Laws of <hi>Noah,</hi> without the observance of which, no Gentile was admitted to be so much as a Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite of the Gate. Considering <hi>Secondly,</hi> what <hi>James</hi> saith, <hi>Act. 15.21.</hi> which was the ground of the decree, Moses <hi>was read every Sabbath day in the Synagogues, where they heard eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Blood forbidden.</hi> Now lest the eating of Blood should be a stumbling-block to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing <hi>Jews,</hi> and hinder their coming in to the Gospel, and an offence to the believing <hi>Jew,</hi> who did not as yet so clearly see the mind of
<pb facs="tcp:38286:5"/>God in that Law, no not (I believe) so long as the Temple stood, the head of the Ceremonial Law; therefore they made those Decrees, and sent them to the Believing Gentiles to forbear <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let the Reader observe <hi>Levit. 17.10.</hi> where the eating of Blood is the most severely prohibited, in the <hi>11 v.</hi> the Lord gives the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Prohibition, the end of it, <hi>The Blood maketh the Atonement for the Soul:</hi> The end was, that men might be kept in Faith and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the Blood of Christ, by which our Atonement is made, <hi>Col. 1.20. Eph. 2.13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Hence <hi>Now,</hi> let them who say that the Blood whereby our Atonement is made with God, is not yet shed, let them, I say, forbear to eat Blood.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Let those that say Christ hath not taken down the Partition-wall (in which Wall, <hi>Blood</hi> was one <hi>Stone)</hi> between Jew and Gentile, <hi>Eph. 2.14.</hi> let them forbear Blood.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Let them that believe some things are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean of themselves, cross to the Apostle, <hi>Rom. 14.14.</hi> and that <hi>Blood</hi> is so, let them forbear Blood.</p>
            <p>But I believe in the Blood of Atonement shed; I believe the Partition-wall is broken down, and that nothing is unclean of it self; therefore I will eat a Blood-pudding, if it be prepared <hi>S. A.</hi> and Bless God for it.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> which you say was
<pb facs="tcp:38286:6"/>never heard of before it was invented in the <hi>Council of Trent;</hi> what gross Ignorance does Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> declare in the <hi>Councils?</hi> let him but read the <hi>Lateran Council</hi> held under Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>3<seg rend="sup">d</seg>,</hi> in the Year <hi>1215.</hi> about three bundred and thirty Years before the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> which began <hi>Anno 1545.</hi> and let him there see if he cannot find <hi>Transubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as well as that Cursed Doctrine of the <hi>Pope's Power to Depose Kings</hi> determined: Yet this is the Man whom his Creatures ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38286:6"/>
            <head>Scripture-Warrant SUFFICIENT PROOF FOR INFANT-BAPTISM: BEING A Reply to Mr. <hi>GRANTHAM</hi>'s <hi>Presumption no Proof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N your Preface to your Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, you tell him, <hi>I hold it no convenient time for Dissenters to write one against another;</hi> why then did you not hold to your own Opinion? but it seems you can hold, and not hold: Or if Mr. <hi>Petto</hi> upon a Schismatical and very Irregular Act of one of your Perswasion in his Church, wrote a small Treatise very soberly to stablish his People in the Lawfulness of Infant-Baptism, and you must therefore write against <hi>him;</hi> yet why must you needs write against <hi>me,</hi> since
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38286:7"/>it was four years, as you tell your Reader, since I wrote that small Treatise upon the Question; which I had not then done, had not one of <hi>yours</hi> required me in way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Justice to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> to Publish- what I had delivered against his Book; nor had I concern'd my self with his Book (for I did grudge the time I spent about it) but that a young Anabaptist, who had been my Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, boasted it was unanswerable.</p>
            <p>In the end of that small Treatise, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded two Questions, (if men would be Writing) to have them answered: In your Preface, you tell your Reader, <hi>They seem to be serious and considerable;</hi> and in <hi>pag.</hi> 2. you tell us, <hi>Some said they were unanswerable;</hi> yet in <hi>pag.</hi> 3. you call the <hi>first an unlearned Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Senties qui vir sum.</note>; how well your great Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing have answered these, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel will declare.</p>
            <p>Before you come to my Question, you tell your Reader, <hi>He playes a little with some Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, rather of other mens devising than his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Argument I borrowed from Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and tell you so, but I improved it another way different from Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and so that all you have said against it signifies nothing; for any other Arguments, I know not one that I have took from others. I have several Books a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Anabaptists sent me, I know not that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38286:7"/>I have read four Leaves in any of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; it's well known I have not time to read Books: <q>I scorn to do as Mr. <hi>Wills</hi> tells Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi> he hath done, to take 43 Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together, for the substance, out of Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> all the while concealing his Name, contrary to the Law of Ingenuity; and calls him therefore <hi>a Notorious Plagiarie.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As for an <hi>Anabaptist,</hi> you tell me, <hi>You know no such Creature,</hi> &amp;c. Though Presumption be no Proof, as you say, yet understanding what your Parents were, I may presume strongly that they would have you baptized when you were an Infant; and if you were then Baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Baptized again afterwards, then I may well joyn the Preposition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist: But you deny your Infant-Baptism (as you do mine) to be Baptism, that was <hi>Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> I shall talk with you about this anon, when I answer for my self.</p>
            <p>You tell me, <hi>I have got Infant-Baptism into a little Corner:</hi> Not so little as your Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> who tells us, <hi>The Elect-regenerate are the subjects of Baptism;</hi> which caused those <hi>Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> you tell me of.</p>
            <p>For Baptism being a visible Ordinance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to a visible Church, visible Believers in Christ, who do not by a scandalous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation give the Lye to their Profession, these with their Seed have a right to the Ordinance of Baptism; and this is not so little a Corner as <hi>Elect-regenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38286:8"/>
            <p>As to what you tell me, <hi>We do not find one Infant in the Jewish Church, nor in any other, during the Apostles dayes, Baptized;</hi> this, with <hi>Where do you find a Positive Command to Baptize Infants?</hi> is the summ of all you can say, and have been answered so often, that it is a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious thing to write any more about it: Yet premising some things, (not stolen out of other Authors, as you falsly charge me) I will give my Answer, though it is very like some have given at least some of the Answers before.</p>
            <p>That some Infants have been under a Church-Ordinance, is agreed on both sides; now what our Lord did in answering the Pharisee's Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion about <hi>Divorce,</hi> I will do the same here: He <hi>Math.</hi> 19.8. leads them to the <hi>Beginning;</hi> so I will go to the <hi>Beginning,</hi> and enquire, how came this about, what was the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it? we find it a <hi>Covenant God made with Abraham and his Seed,</hi> Gen. 17.7. Here's the <hi>Beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me with humble Reverence to that Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous Majesty, conceive the great God thus Treating with <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> thou (with thy Father <hi>Terah</hi>) livest here in <hi>Mesopotamia</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.2.</note>, among Idolaters, and thou servest other gods as they do
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Josh.</hi> 24.2, 14, 15.</note>; but from my own free Love to thee
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.37.</note>, I that am the only living and true God do
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38286:8"/>now appear unto thee
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.2.</note>: Come out of <hi>Haran,</hi> and follow me to a Land which I will shew thee; there will I bless thee, make thee a Blessing; yea, so bless thee, that in thee shall all Families of the Earth be blessed
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3.</note>: And though I am the absolute Sovereign of the whole World, and need not be tied to any Creature, yet for the sake of him that shall come from thee according to the flesh
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5.</note>, in whom all the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies shall be blessed; I will make a Covenant with thee
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4.</note>, and not only with thee, but I will make an everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant to be a God to thee and thy Seed
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</note>; yea, with thy little ones
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.11, 12, 13.</note>, they shall be mine
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20.21.</note>: And though you may trust me upon my Word, yet to tye my self more sure to thee and thy Seed, and to strengthen your Faith in my Covenant, I will add a Seal to my Covenant, and this shall be administred to thy Seed when they are but eight dayes old
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 11, 12.</note>: To your seed will I give my Statutes and my Judgments, which I will not do to other Nations
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 147.19, 20.</note>: Now upon my dealing thus with your Seed, I require that they shall cleave only to me their God, and have nothing to do with the gods of the other Nations about them: Observe the Statutes and Judgments
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38286:9"/>which I shall give them
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12, 20. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.13.</note> And as for me, I know your Seed shall meet with abundance of troubles; but as they have me an All-suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent God
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</note> in Covenant with them, so in all their troubles, be they National or Personal, be they Bodily, be they Spiritual, let them look no further than their God in Covenant with them. If any of them sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, as be sure they will, and their Consciences accuse them, and fill them with the fears of my Wrath, let them repent, and lay hold upon me in this Covenant, and they shall find me a merciful God, pardoning Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Transgression and Sin
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>Mica.</hi> 7.18. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12. <hi>He humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self greatly before the God of his Fathers;</hi> with whom God was in Covenant.</note>: Are any of them afflicted and wounded with the vileness and corruption of their Hearts, they cannot purge them, they cannot love me, and walk with me as they would do? let them come to me their God in Covenant, consider the Seal of my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and I their God can and will help them: I will circumcise their Hearts to love me
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> what I do with thee and thy Seed, the same will I do with others that are not thy Seed after the flesh, but they own and give up themselves to me thy God, and shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep my Statutes, as I require of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38286:9"/>thee and thy Seed, they shall partake, and their Seed with them, of the same Covenant, and Seal of my Covenant which thou doest
<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 17.12, 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Many Believers in Christ <hi>to</hi> come, there were before <hi>Abraham,</hi> why did not God make this Covenant with <hi>Enoch, Noah,</hi> or some others of them? What is that to us? <hi>Elihu</hi> tells us, <hi>Job</hi> 33.13. <hi>He giveth not account of any of his matters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have the <hi>beginning</hi> where the Lord expresly declares the Seed of Believing <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> to be visible members of the visible Church with him, sealing both Him and Them with the same seal of the Covenant, which was made both with Him and Them. If God hath now since Christ is come, nulled and repealed this Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, I say, if this can be infallibly proved, the controversie between us and the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists is at an end; for then, no Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, no Seal.</p>
            <p>But this the Anabaptists must prove by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press</hi> Scriptures, else we shall not believe them. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They require of us <hi>positive command,</hi> to administer the Seal of the Covenant to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. Baptism is a Seal of the Covenant of Grace: Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed was no Covenant of Works I am sure. To be <hi>a God to a Soul,</hi> is the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38286:10"/>God can go; there is nothing above God. This is wont to be called <hi>Anima Faederis,</hi> the Soul of the Covenant of Grace; remove the Covenant then first by <hi>express Scriptures.</hi> They who will buy by one Bushel, and sell by a less, we know what we call them in English. If you will buy by <hi>express</hi> and <hi>positive</hi> weights, then sell by such weight.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God never made any Covenant with his people, but if he repealed the Covenant, he did it himself <hi>expresly,</hi> and not leave it to us to prove the repealing of it by <hi>consequences,</hi> which we frame.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) He makes a Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) He makes a Covenant with <hi>Israel,</hi> Deut. 5.2, 3. <hi>God made a Covenant with us in Horeb, God made not this Covenant with our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but with us,</hi> Exod. 20. and <hi>Ch.</hi> 24.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) God made another Covenant with <hi>Israel,</hi> in the Land of <hi>Moab,</hi> beside the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant he made with them in <hi>Horeb, Deut.</hi> 29.1. from 9. to the 16. <hi>v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Covenant made at <hi>Horeb,</hi> or <hi>Sinai,</hi> the Lord <hi>expresly</hi> repeals it, <hi>Hob.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Now that which decayeth and waxeth old, is ready to vanish away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Covenant in <hi>Exodus,</hi> and <hi>Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomy;</hi> when this people <hi>rejected</hi> the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Seed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Lord Jesus, <hi>Away with him, Crucifie him,</hi> Luke 23.18, 21. and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38286:10"/>continued in hardness and unbelief, God breaks his Covenant with them, <hi>expresly,</hi> Zech. 11.10. This Covenant of God with them, was their <hi>Beauty. This staffe cut asunder, that I might break my Covenant, which I had made with all the people.</hi> Rom. 11.19, 20. <hi>The Branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es were broken off because of unbelief.</hi> Hos. 1.9. <hi>Call his name</hi> Lo-ammi, <hi>for ye are not my people, and I will not be your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. But with whom did God break this Covenant? <hi>not with the poor of the flock,</hi> who believed in Christ, <hi>and waited upon him,</hi> Zech. 11.11. Not with those whom he had <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Feed, v.</hi> 7. The little remnant with whom the Covenant stood firm, thô the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Nation were rejected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor doth he break this Covenant with the <hi>Children first,</hi> but he cast off the <hi>Parents first,</hi> and with them their Children.</p>
            <p>As for the Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> actually believing in <hi>Christ come,</hi> that God indeed will continue to be their God, and seal the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to them, as he was and did before, but not to their seed, as he was and did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ came, name the Scripture that <hi>expresly</hi> speaketh this.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. If God hath repealed this Covenant with Believers Seed, then <hi>Paul</hi> was quite out, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. in his setting forth the miserable state of us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> compared with the <hi>Jews,</hi> viz. <hi>That we were strangers from the Covenants
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38286:11"/>of Promise.</hi> And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. amongst the Priviledges the Jewish Church had, the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants</hi> are numbred for one; and among those Covenants I am sure this with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed is one; yea the Covenant and the Seal are so conjoyn'd, that the Seal is called the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.8. But as for us, not <hi>one</hi> Covenant did ever God make with us, thô three times at least, we find him Covenanting with them. But it seems that part of our misery is still upon us, and not only so, but the believing <hi>Jews</hi> themselves have this misery befallen them by embracing Christ, as to their Seed, from which they were free before: They have lost their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, and their Children as well as ours, are now become, <hi>Strangers to the Covenants of Promise:</hi> But will any man that is not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, but believes the Scriptures; say, that <hi>Paul</hi> was out, he err'd in this.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. There is such a dishonour offered to Christ, that he by his Sacrifice should <hi>break down the middle wall of Partition,</hi> Eph. 2.14, 15. between the <hi>Jews</hi> and us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>make of twain, One;</hi> and now set up the Partition wall between the Believing <hi>Jew</hi> and his Seed, and make of <hi>One, twain,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding between the root and the branch, and now their Seed are no part of the <hi>House, v.</hi> 19. So expresly contrary to the discourse of the Apostle from the 13th. <hi>v.</hi> to the end
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38286:11"/>of the <hi>Chapter,</hi> that unless God had <hi>expresly</hi> revealed it (then I am sure these verses had never been written) they must be given up to a strange Delusion, that can receive these <hi>Anabaptists</hi> Doctrine.</p>
            <p>From these grounds I answer, to <hi>your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitive Command to baptize Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) There was no need that Christ should give any such Command. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is nothing more in Baptism, which should make Children Subjects more uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of receiving it, and us to Administer it to them, than was in Circumcision.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All Christs Apostles were <hi>Jews,</hi> bred up in the Jewish Church, and they knew very well the Covenant of God with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his Seed, and what their daily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice was in Administring Circumcision to Infants, a Seal to the same Covenant that Baptism is.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Infants now have as much need of the benefits signified and sealed in Baptism, as they had then under Circumcision.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The business then, and what took up the minds of the Apostles, was not baptizing of Infants, as how to bring men over to the Faith of the Gospel, to believe in this Christ, the promised Seed; they who did believe in Christ, did declare their Faith in him, by being baptized into him: But <hi>believing</hi> was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38286:12"/>the business above <hi>baptizing.</hi> So the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Christ sent me not to Baptize, but to Preach the Gospel:</hi> That Baptizing of Adult Persons, was not the thing they so much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in, as to have men believe in Christ, thò they did baptize Believers, 'tis true.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Had the Apostles removed Circumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and left no ordinance for their Infants in the room of it, but shut the door against them, who had been a thousand years in the Church with their Parents under an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; this would have been an Objection of weight against the Apostles, and hindered the Gospel spreading; they should have heard of it with both ears, and we should have read of it, who read so much what a stir there was for removing, and changing a Bloody and Painful Ordinance for a Better.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We read of the Baptizing of whole Housholds. Children use to be reckoned as members of <hi>our</hi> Houses, they were of <hi>Gods</hi> House once, and are still, if I mistake not the Text, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.19. While <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, We Gentiles who were before <hi>Aliens from the Common-wealth of</hi> Israel, <hi>v.</hi> 12. (and were not Children then members of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Israel?</hi>) are now <hi>fellow Citizens — and of the Houshold God.</hi> And it is much that in all the Housholds <hi>Paul</hi> baptized, there should be no Children.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Baptizing of the Children of Proselites
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38286:12"/>in their admission into the Jewish Church, Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> (a great searcher into the practices of that Church) tells us, was so known, so frequent, and usual, that there is scarce any thing more known and usual. And if so, no wonder thô we read nothing of the Baptizing of Infants; the Baptizing of the Parents who were not so, that is chiefly Recorded, and their Baptizing into the Christian Faith.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) As there was no need of a new po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitive Command, so had our Lord intended that the Seed of the <hi>Jews</hi> believing in Christ now come, should be denied to be visible mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, as they were before, and debarred from the initiating ordinance which they had before; I am assured and confident, he would have declared <hi>it expresly.</hi> It being so contrary to <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant, under which all his Seed had lived to this day, wherein Christ suffered from <hi>Abrahams</hi> time. <hi>In him all the Nations of the Earth shall be blessed,</hi> he told <hi>Abraham;</hi> and is this <hi>a blessing,</hi> to turn all our Seed out of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and deny then the Seal of it to them, which we enjoyed before he suffered? Verily, he that was so careful to remove a Mosai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Law out of the way, about the eating of unclean Creatures, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.14, 15, 16. that it might not be a stumbling block to <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:38286:13"/>now going to the Gentiles, and by this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal of that Law, the <hi>Jews</hi> might admit, and eat Swines flesh at their Table; would he I say be so clear and express, to tell the <hi>Jews,</hi> they might bring a <hi>Hog into their House,</hi> and would he not be as clear and express, in turning the Seed of <hi>Abraham out of his House,</hi> in which they had been longer than <hi>Moses</hi> Law against Hogs, and deny them the Seal of his Covenant, which so long they had enjoyed? Let any considerate man who is not miserably blinded, judge.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) From that Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Claude,</hi> a very learned French-man, and Sufferer in this last French-Persecution, but now dead, answered his Popish adversary, telling him, <hi>That remaining in the Principles of his Sect, he could have no rational assurance of the validity of his Baptism; that the Baptism of Infants was good, and that the Anabaptists were in an Errour, hence he must return to the Communion with the Church of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>He tells him, he need say but a word to that, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>This Scripture,</hi> saith he, <hi>hath clearly established Infant. Baptism. For since Baptism ought to be given to them to whom the Promise is made, and that is made to our Children as well as to us, it ought to be given not only to us, but unto our Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Mr. <hi>Grif.</hi> told us this was no <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38286:13"/>to baptize, but an <hi>encouragement.</hi> But I pray do the Scriptures use to encourage us to that, which is not our Duty? When God made that <hi>Everlasting Covenant</hi> as he calls it, between <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, there is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand strict enough given to Seal it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9, 10, 11, 14. And thô the Seal be changed, as the Worship of God in the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is changed from what it was in the Old Testament; yet the second Command binds us to observe it, and keep it pure; so that command binds us to Seal the Covenant, <hi>v.</hi> 9. for he calls the Seal the Covenant.</p>
            <p>And because the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Children, is used in this Text, I shall give the Reader no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice how you would cheat him, in telling him the signification of the Word, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Offspring of growth or Stature, but</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies an Infant;</hi> say you. But does it signifie <hi>onely</hi> so; you would perswade your Reader so, telling him <hi>but</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>signifies an Infant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Reader that hath skill in the Greek tongue, see where the word is the first time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>used in the New Testament, <hi>Math.</hi> 2.18. Did <hi>Rachel</hi> weep only for her Children <hi>of growth and Stature?</hi> what age these Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were of, <hi>v.</hi> 16. tells us, from <hi>two years old,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not any above two, but <hi>under</hi> two <hi>downwards,</hi> if to a fortnight or week old; thus again, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.7. as a Nurse cherisheth her <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Children. What
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38286:14"/>onely her Children <hi>of growth and stature?</hi> I told over two and twenty Texts more where the word is used properly, and sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>little</hi> Children as well as Children of <hi>growth;</hi> and two or three of them princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, little Children; and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies onely an <hi>Infant;</hi> then <hi>Timothy</hi> knew the Scriptures when he was an Infant, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Thô this word we never contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
            <p>Thus you do with the word <hi>Baptize;</hi> but of this in its place.</p>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>NOw I come to my <hi>unlearned</hi> Question, as you call it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Since God was so gracious to make a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed, and it did then consist with his Wisdom to constitute his Church of Parents and Children, while the Parents did Believe in Christ</hi> to <hi>come; why may it not consist with his Grace to continue that Covenant, and with his Wisdom still to constitute his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel Church of Parents and Children, the</hi> Jews <hi>now believing in Christ,</hi> come?</p>
               <p>I might have added in my Question, <hi>that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38286:14"/>Covenant Sealed</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 17.9. <hi>Will force it seems to carry, If no Seal no Covenant, the Seal being called the Covenant.</hi>
                  </note>; but Mr. <hi>Tombs,</hi> who is the strongest adversary to Infant-Baptism that ever wrote, he yields that if Children be members of the Church with Parents, then they must be Baptized; for <hi>I grant</hi> (saith he) <hi>that Baptism is the way and manner of so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Admission into the Church, I mean the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular way.</hi> And we were told by one of this party, <hi>that Baptism is the</hi> Form <hi>of a Church;</hi> and would bear us down that Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> hath delivered the same, and this he urged with great zeal.</p>
               <p>If then no Baptism, no Church: for <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma est causa per quam res est, id quod est.</hi> The same Person denied all Baptism but by <hi>Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping:</hi> Whence it follows clearly, there are no Churches in the world, but these <hi>Dipt Churches;</hi> hence they deny Communion with all Churches, for they want the <hi>Form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me before I come to consider his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, to adde one Scripture more besides what I have mentioned before, that is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28, 29. which speaks of these <hi>Jews</hi> broken off. <hi>Touching the Election</hi> (I conceive thô it be true as to eternal Election, yet that is not here properly meant, but that choice of them for his peculiar people, which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> mentions twice together, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6, 7.) <hi>they are beloved</hi> (with a Love of good will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38286:15"/>to them still) <hi>for their Fathers sake</hi> (not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of them, <hi>but because he loved thy Fathers,</hi> Deut. 4.37. And because he made his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with their Fathers to be a God to them, and their Seed, which these <hi>Jews</hi> are; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Fathers, <hi>even in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daies if they return to the Lord their God
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Return they shall.</hi> Rom. 11.26. 2 Cor. 3.16.</note>, he will not forget the Covenant of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>) Deut. 4.30, 31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the gifts and calling of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 29. Take the words with respect to the <hi>Jews</hi> of whom he spake before, choosing and Adopt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Posterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and engaging himself by Covenant to them, are inviolable; their Priviledges shall be as high as ever, not shut out of the Church from their Parents, and denied an Ordinance, as now the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists do.</p>
               <p>I demanded a Scripture to prove, it doth not consist with the Grace and Wisdom of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have given you several Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, after the Constitution of the Church in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and you tell me of <hi>a Covenant of grace made with the whole world in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised Seed to</hi> Adam, <hi>and that</hi> Adam, Noah <hi>and all little Children lived under a Covenant of Grace more than</hi> 2000. <hi>years, during all which time no Infant</hi> (you might as well say neither <hi>Adam,</hi> or <hi>Noah) was concern'd in Circumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Baptism, and yet were as much of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38286:15"/>Church as was needful for their Salvation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And to what purpose is all this? your learned answer to my unlearned question sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies nothing. Was that my Question, <hi>Whether there were any Covenant of grace before this with Ahraham? or whether any were saved before A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams Covenant?</hi> I pray Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> study your Logick better, and understand what that fallacie <hi>Ignoratio Elenchi</hi> is, which now is yours, before you make such a noise of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting Doctors out of the room.</p>
               <p>One word about <hi>Noah,</hi> then I will tell you what my Question is. If by <hi>Noah</hi>'s Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant you understand a Covenant of Grace, I am not clear in that: I take that to be a Covenant with all the Creatures as well as with <hi>Noah,</hi> that God will drown the world no more: So the Rainbow which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears with rain, is both a sign and seal of this Covenant. God use to seal his Covenants. But why should God make a Covenant and seal it with Creatures that do not understand it? Read our first Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.10. And you shall find this: <hi>The Covenant of God may be made with, and the Seal of the Covenant applyed to Creatures that have not the use of reason; which may serve to refute the Anabaptists fancy in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Administration of Baptism no Infants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence I put the Attribute of <hi>Wisdom,</hi> as well as <hi>Grace</hi> into my question, because the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38286:16"/>Arguments which the Anabaptists bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Infant-baptism, do as much strike at the wisdom of God, in making a Covenant with the seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be Circumcised on the eighth day. What? to make a Covenant with them that doe not understand it? to Circumcise and seal a Covenant with them at eight days old, when they do not understand it? what to have children members of the Church with parents, when they do not understand it? Let them stay for this Covenant, Circumsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and Church-membership, till they be rather <hi>eighteen</hi> years old, that they may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand these things, and see whether they do believe, repent, and walk as their Father did with God; then admit them. This is the Anabaptists wisdom in denying Infant-Baptism.</p>
               <p>Now I come to my question, and shall make it appear your answer signifies nothing. You tell me of a <hi>Covenant of grace made with the whole world in the promised seed to Adam,</hi> &amp;c. I tell <hi>you,</hi> while <hi>Adam, Noah,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> lived under that Covenant made with the <hi>whole world,</hi> God was pleased to make a Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and with none other but <hi>Abraham,</hi> that <hi>he would be his God, and the God of his Seed, and sealed this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: by which Covenant God did separate, and Divide all Abrahams seed from the world, living
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38286:16"/>under that Covenant you speak of.</hi> Hence we poor Gentiles believing in Christ, are called <hi>Abrahams Seed, Gal.</hi> 3.29. not <hi>Adam</hi>'s Seed. Hence <hi>Abraham</hi> is called the <hi>Father of all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers</hi> three times in <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.16.18. not <hi>Adam,</hi> nor <hi>Noah.</hi> Hence believing Gentiles, are said to be <hi>grafted into Abrahams stock, Rom.</hi> 11.17. not into <hi>Adam</hi>'s, nor <hi>Noah</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>Hence my question is, By what Scripture warrant you Reduce our children into the State of the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> or <hi>Noah, &amp;c.</hi> since we are never called any of their Children, but only <hi>Abrahams;</hi> whose seed differ from theirs by a special Covenant made with them, and sealed to them? To which of them did God say, I will <hi>be the God of thy Seed, and I will seal to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now suppose that were true, which is the great business of your Pomphlet, to prove, <hi>That all Infants dying such are saved;</hi> that thereby you might take off the <hi>Odium</hi> which lyes upon you, for shutting the Children of Believers out of the Church, and denying them Baptism, they being all under a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace made with <hi>Adam,</hi> as you say; yet tell me,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is this Covenant of God with <hi>Abraham</hi>'s seed in <hi>Vain?</hi> does the Holy One make vain Covenants? As to his Seed, they were well enough before under <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant; if they dye, or if <hi>Isaac</hi> dye before he be eight daies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38286:17"/>old he is saved, so that this Covenant might have been spared.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If their seed dye while little ones, I hope they are not further from Salvation by this Covenant, nor have Parents the lesse hope of their Salvation by it, but I think much more. Two strings to a bow are good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Doth God discover his Grace to Sinners more than needs? I am sure this Covenant, and Seal manifest Grace.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Can poor, lost, undone Sinners have too many waies to lay hold upon a Holy, Just God, when they are under their fears and sense of Sin? And have not the Seed of Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers one way to lay hold upon God by this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with their believing Parents, when their hearts would be returning to God? I appeal to all judicious Christians, sound in Judgment, and upright in heart. As to the experience I have found, and declared it to others, you make a scoffe at me. <hi>p.</hi> 6. I will be with you by and by, Mr. <hi>Grantham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet again, as to that notion wherein you so much glory, and have made five remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Demonstrations,</hi> as you call them, to prove it; you must make three more Demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or else these five will not do the feat.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God saves those who are under that Covenant, without any <hi>Condition;</hi> that Covenant having no Condition in it. Name
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38286:17"/>the Text I pray. Some of yours have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. but the <hi>Righteousness of Christ</hi> mentioned in that Text, is the <hi>material</hi> or <hi>meritorious cause</hi> of our justification from all Sin, <hi>Adams Sin, Original Sin,</hi> and <hi>Actual Sin.</hi> But how this righteousness comes to be <hi>Ours,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Condition, or not, it speaks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. So that from that Text an <hi>Infant</hi> can argue no more for its Justification and Salvation, than an <hi>Adult</hi> person. It onely tells us there is such <hi>a righteousness provided by Christ,</hi> by which we are justified, but if it be not imputed to us, neither Infant nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult person is the better. How it comes to be <hi>Ours,</hi> other Texts tells us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. &amp;c. 2. If we be justified from <hi>Adams</hi> Sin <hi>onely,</hi> are we then <hi>justified to life,</hi> as the Text speaks? I think not. I Suppose we shall find some other Sin in Infants tho' Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers deny it.</p>
               <p>Hence Mr. <hi>Griffiin,</hi> when he had told me, <hi>tho' I was an old Man, yet I might learn;</hi> very true, Mr. <hi>Griffin,</hi> but what shall I learn? This? <hi>God saves Infants dying such,</hi> out <hi>of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</hi> Not <hi>by</hi> it; or <hi>under</hi> it, but <hi>out</hi> of it? This was News indeed, I never heard it before, nor believe it after: But by this, he avoids (if it were true) Faith and Repentance, the Conditions of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:38286:18"/>2. You must Demonstrate, that by this Covenant he saves those who have lost the Image of God, and are corrupt by nature, for Infant Regeneration, and Heart Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cising is denyed by yours, and you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You must Demonstrate, that tho' In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants have not actually sinned, against the Covenant of Grace, yet they have not Unbelief and Impenitency <hi>seminally,</hi> which are quite opposite to the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p>You ask, at the end of your first Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, p. 21. <hi>As for poor Infants, what evil have they done?</hi> but I ask,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How are Infants <hi>born?</hi> [of this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do you ask what have they done? Did you never see <hi>Revenge, Wrath, Pride, Envy, Self-Love, Rebellion against, and striking of Parents,</hi> acting in little Children? Blessed <hi>Austin</hi> observed a sucking Child, that was not able to articulate a word, look with a Countenance even pale with envie upon his fellow suckling, which shared with him in the same milk; which made that Holy Man cry out, <hi>Ʋbi Domine? quando Domine?</hi> Where was the <hi>Place,</hi> when was the <hi>Time,</hi> that I was an Innocent Creature?</p>
               <p>Yes, Sir, Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> will tell you, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are innocent.</hi> p. 13. This is the first part of your Answer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then you come to a Second, and that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38286:18"/>is, by putting a Question to me; therein tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, my <hi>unlearned Question is guilty of no more Reason than this: Since God was so Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and it did consist with his Wisdom, to give</hi> Abraham <hi>a Command to offer up his beloved Son, as a sign of Christ to Come; why may it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist with his Grace and Wisdom, for us of our own heads, without any Command from God, to offer up every one his dearest Child, in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that Christ is come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ay, now you stitch it, Mr. <hi>Grantham;</hi> you tell me, <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>That I was asleep when I was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized:</hi> You do so <hi>jog</hi> me, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> with these words, <hi>Fables, Fancy, Conceit,</hi> and your <hi>Scoffs,</hi> with which you are pleased to fill up your Lines, that I think I shall be awake by that time I come at it, to Answer it: But for the present, you have laid such a Question to mine, to illustrate how much <hi>Reason my Question was guilty of,</hi> that if when you laid your Pieces together to make up any Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you did not lay them more even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, you were but a plain <hi>Botcher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come, lay the Questions together.</p>
               <p n="1">1. My Question is about a Gracious Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, lay your Question to it, Is it a Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Covenant? Did God give this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Abraham</hi> to offer up <hi>Isaac,</hi> that it should be an Example to us, to cut our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Throats when he commands it? Did God ever command others to do it? But God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38286:19"/>made this Covenant with all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and strictly commanded them all to keep the Seal of it, upon the danger of Cutting them off else, as <hi>Moses</hi> had like to have found it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How do you prove that the end of God in Commanding <hi>Abraham</hi> to offer his Son, was, that it should be <hi>a Sign of Christ to come?</hi> the Text saith plainly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.1. <hi>The Lord tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Abraham:</hi> The end was to try <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Obedience; whence <hi>v.</hi> 12. he saith, <hi>Now I know thou fearest God.</hi> 2. If so, then <hi>Isaac</hi>'s Throat must have been Cut and dye: As all the Sacrifices which did typifie Christ, they were all killed; though it was in his <hi>Will,</hi> so it was in Christs <hi>Will,</hi> and Actually done.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Gods Act towards <hi>Abraham</hi> in this Case was an Act of meer <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> but his Act in my Question was an Act of meer <hi>Grace:</hi> You say so indeed, but 'tis not true, it was a great Tempting of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. There is a vast difference between a <hi>Command</hi> and a <hi>Promise:</hi> In my Question it runs thus, <hi>Abraham, I will be thy God and Isaac</hi>'s <hi>God;</hi> in your Question it is, <hi>Abraham, go Cut Isaac</hi>'s <hi>Throat:</hi> A great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween what <hi>God will</hi> do and <hi>we should</hi> do.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Come we then to <hi>Circumcision,</hi> which was a painful Ordinance, and therein the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of God and his Command did appear; yet considering it as it was a Seal added to the Covenant, and did thereby help to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38286:19"/>their Faith, in the Grace and Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of God, so it was also an Act of Grace; insomuch that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> did glory in it, and did reproach the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that had it not, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.6. and 17.26. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They did so prize it, that it made a heavy stir in the Churches, when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles went about to remove it; and to this day they do tenaciously retain it.</p>
               <p>To Conclude, my Question is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an everlasting Covenant, proceeding from the pure Grace of God, comfortable to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, comfortable and advantageous to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oor Children, when they come to understand it; with a strict Command to have this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant upon their hearts, by impressing the Seal of it upon their Children in all their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; which Covenant was never repealed to this day, and therefore that being in force, there is still a Seal belonging to it; which Seal is Baptism, in the room of Circumcision, as is clear, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
               <p>[As for your Carping at the Word, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Circumcise,</hi> I have spoken to it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.]</p>
               <p>Your Question is grounded upon a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Command of God given to <hi>Ahraham</hi> in particular, without any Command to his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity to observe; nor ever was observed, but only by <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:38286:20"/>
               <p>Now, how this Question of yours serves to demonstrate the <hi>little Reason my Question is guilty of,</hi> as you tell me, let all men judge.</p>
               <p>The next three Paragraphs afford but little to take notice of: For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. As for our keeping our Baptized Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren so long from the Lords Table, I hope they must first be able to <hi>Discern the Lords Body,</hi> and to <hi>Examine themselves,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.28, 29. Though the Children were Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised at eight dayes old, yet they were not to eat the Passover till they came to such years of discretion, as to understand the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Ordinance; therefore their Fathers did teach them the meaning of it, when they took up the Lamb. But our Question is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Initiating Ordinance,</hi> we would have our Children under that betimes, under a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Covenant sealed. God would not have them stay above eight dayes, unless the Child were Sick: And why <hi>eight?</hi> we let the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish reasons alone, leaving it with his Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. God lays claim to them betimes; they are <hi>Mine,</hi> Ezek. 16.21. I and they are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Sensible things, as their Afflictions in <hi>Egypt</hi> were, and set forth in the bitter Herbs which they eat, were sooner under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by Children, than spiritual things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas he saith, <hi>Repentance and Faith were required of those who were Baptized:</hi> Very true, of Adult Persons, with whom <hi>Peter</hi> was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38286:20"/>Treating, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. who had Crucified that Christ in whom they now were to believe, and into whose Name they were to be Baptized, well might he call for Repentance. When <hi>Philip</hi> Baptized the Eunuch, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37. <hi>If thou Believest,</hi> &amp;c. in the Messiah <hi>now</hi> come: So was <hi>Abraham</hi> a Believer in Christ <hi>to</hi> come, before this Covenant was made with him and his Seed: <hi>Isaac</hi> was reputed with his Father a Believer in Christ, when he was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised. So I have taught, and it was my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, when I claimed the Covenant for my Child, and so dedicated my Child to him; to examine my Covenant-Interest, my Faith and Repentance, as well as if I were going to the Lords Supper; but that actual Faith and Repentance are required of Infants <hi>before</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, I know no Text nor Reasou, more than before Circumcision.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He saith, <hi>We do not deny Infants to be of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, that is the <hi>Church</hi> I would fain have Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> define, and tell us where it is: So far as I can learn by his Book, <hi>It is a Company of Innocents, without Sin, without Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances;</hi> (for so he speaks of Infants, as we shall see anon) but what next, I know not; nor do I know Churches without Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; where the Gospel speaks of such, I keep my self to the revealed will of God, leaving secret things to him.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:38286:21"/>
               <p>Let him tell us how the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which comes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ab evocando;</hi> because the Church is <hi>a Company Called out from the rest,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> knows, being a learned Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. How this agrees with this Innocent and Sinless Company, to be <hi>Called out!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you ask me, how it agrees with our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized little ones to be <hi>Called?</hi> I Answer. By being Branches of such a root as is called out of the World, they are called with him the Root and Branches going together, and they Members of the same Church with their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents under Ordinances. As <hi>Isaac</hi> was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Person called out in his Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who was called out from the Idolaters, and was Circumcised under the same Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance with his Father.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Gospel gives to Parents and Children the same denomination: The Church is <hi>a Company of Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. So the Children of these Saints are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>But now they are Saints,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: To Interpret this of <hi>Legitimacy,</hi> is so gross and absurd a Conceit, that I wonder it should come into any rational mans Thoughts: I have spoken to this in my little Treatise, and many other worthy Divines before me, have given the sense very clear and plain; but when God will blind mens eyes, (when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will shut their eyes against the Light) how shall they see? But this Text will also warrant our Practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:38286:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HAving done with my first Question, you say, <hi>Let us hear your second Question;</hi> you shall Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> 'tis this.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>If God hath repealed his Covenant with the believing</hi> Jews <hi>seed, turned their Children out of the Church, and deny them Baptism, though the</hi> Jews <hi>truly believe in Christ come; What hath God left in the room of these, that carry any shew of his Blessing, or good will towards their Children during their Infant-state?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you tell your Reader, there is Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity in the Words, <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Church:</hi> None at all, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> you know the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and what the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was. You say, <hi>That I yield they were in the Covenant, and Church-members, before they were Circumcised:</hi> Very true, I hope we do not set our Seals before our Covenants; first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, then Seal. Also, if they were not Members of the Church, they should not have the Priviledge of the Church; only their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bership is Compleated and Declared, when the Initiating Seal is applyed to them. As it is in Corporations, the eldest Son of a Free-man,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38286:22"/>born in the Corporation, was a Member, and had a right to Freedom, but not compleat, nor acted till he took his Oath; so the High Priest, <hi>Levit.</hi> 4.3. was not a compleat High Priest, till he was Anointed.</p>
               <p>Then you come to tell me, what Priviledges the <hi>Jews</hi> Infants have now.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <hi>They were free from their Jewish Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state,</hi> Gal. 5.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. What is this to the Infant that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands nothing of it, but was in as safe an Estate before, yea, and better? that <hi>Freedom</hi> is nothing to it while an Infant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. And they were free from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, <hi>That God was now none of their God, and also from a Seal of that Covenant:</hi> This is a Priviledge with a witness; do you and yours take it for me and mine. O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Priviledge! Do you call this <hi>Freedom?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <hi>They are devoted to God, by the Prayers of the Church; warranted therein by the example of Christ, when little Children were brought to him, — And accordingly we dedicate them to God, according to our Capacity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. If Praying for Children be a <hi>Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of them, then almost fifty years I have been <hi>Dedicating</hi> of Children to God; but I read of no Dedication that lasted one Month together in the Word. What, are you the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38286:22"/>People that only Devote and Dedicate your Children to God? I hope others as well as you, Pray and Fast for them as well as you. Do you think that <hi>Abraham,</hi> and those Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men of old did not pray for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as well as Circumcise them? A pitiful answer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the example of Christ, it seems he will bless them; and blessed be his name he will do it. But one thing here, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> I must put you in mind of, which I forgot, when you answered my first Question; <hi>Viz. Christ did not appoint those very Infants who were brought to him, to have his Ordinances im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon them,</hi> say you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Very true, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> because they were under Ordinances already; these were <hi>Jews</hi> Children, not <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he was not sent to them as yet, nor must his Apostles go among them yet: As for <hi>Christian Baptism</hi> it was not yet instituted, and would you have him impose it before the institution.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>You tell me, by the Blessing of Education, some Children of</hi> 7. <hi>or</hi> 8. <hi>years old, have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to more knowledge, and experience of the Work of Grace, who yet were never sprinckled, than multitudes of</hi> 70, <hi>or</hi> 80 <hi>years who were sprinkled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> As for your word <hi>sprinkling,</hi> I will talk with you anon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And of those Children who were cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38286:23"/>multitudes of them, thô they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not to such a knowledge of Christ; (he was not then so clearly revealed to their Fathers) yet for Knowledge and saving Grace, they had it as early as yours every whit; for all that we read of, that were godly in Scripture, were so from their Childhood; we read only of <hi>Manasseh,</hi> that was convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when Adult. So among us, many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants baptized, before and since your Errour rose up to trouble the peace of the Churches, and to be an inlet to other Errours; I say many Instances might be given of Children that before the age you mention, have discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the sparklings of Grace. Old Mr. <hi>Blacker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> that man of God, when he preached the Funeral Sermon for his own Daughter, Mr. <hi>Faircloughs</hi> first Wife, gave this Testimony of her, That from three years old, she did sincerely fear God. A Child of four years old of a Neighbour by me, when it went to School to learn its letters, when it came from School, would often go to the Father with these words, Father, I Love God, I love my Father, I love my Mother; but always first, I love God; the Child falls sick, the Mother asked it, Art willing to dye? Yes, said the Child, I will go lye in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som. A Minister dining there, and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thanks after dinner, the Child lying in the Cradle by, of its own accord lifted up
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38286:23"/>its hands, while he was speaking, when he had done, let fall its hands and died. You that tell us, God does not circumcise the Hearts of Children, because they cannot love him: God confutes you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I deny not but God doth overlook the Infirmities of his People, and his Grace is Free, and so works in what Children he please.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But still you declare a slighting of the Grace of God in that Covenant of God with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, which we do reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and bless his Name for; you take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that which is comfortable to godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and to poor Children be sure a great advantage; reducing the Children of the soundest believing <hi>Jews,</hi> into the same state with their Children who are the haters of Christ at this day.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) The third Priviledge you tell me, is this, <hi>Our gracious God by Jesus Christ hath left us an open Declaration, that the Kingdom of Heaven belongs to Infants; in which Declaration he hath not excepted so much as one of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. What is this to the Infant state of the believing <hi>Jew,</hi> when as the <hi>Jew</hi> that hates Christ at this day may say, This is as much Comfort to me; thô I hate and abhor to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in your <hi>Messiah,</hi> and my Child is in as hopeful state as yours: yea so are all <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Mahumetans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:38286:24"/>2. What, doth our Lord d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>are, <hi>That all the Infants of the World dying such, are members of the Kingdom of Glory?</hi> It is not all one to say, <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven consists, as of Adult Persons, so, of little Infants;</hi> and to say, <hi>All Infants are members of the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> these two Propositions differ, Mr. <hi>Grantham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If it be true, it was true before God Covenanted with <hi>Abraham</hi> to be the God of his Seed; surely there was some benefit to <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, more than was in that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant you talk of, else the Covenant was in vain. <hi>Did God say to</hi> Adam, <hi>I am the God of thee and thy Seed, and I will Seal my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with thee, and thy Seed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. What Comfort is this to the Seed of a believing <hi>Jew,</hi> when grown up, and hath the Sense of Sin and Apprehensions of the anger of God against him? <hi>Comfort?</hi> O what a <hi>Torment</hi> doth this prove to think, When I was an Infant if I had died, I had been sav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: O that I had died then, but now I am grown up I shall be damned! so that 'tis a great misery to mankind, that God lets them live beyond the state of Infants; for let them dye while Infants they are all saved, and what Parent that wisheth the happiness of Children, would not say, Let all my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dye while they are Infants, for then they are Innocent; if Mr. <hi>Granthams</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine be true; they should never sin against
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38286:24"/>God, and certainly be saved. But the Child of a Believing <hi>Jew</hi> grown up, and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science awakened, now repenting hath a God in Covenant with him by <hi>Abrahams</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to lay hold upon. Only Mr. <hi>Granthams</hi> Wisdom scoffs at it.</p>
               <p>These be your privileges; and now you adde, <hi>From all which you may see, God hath left us in the room of Circumcision</hi> (and of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of being their God; why is this left out and Circumcision onely put in? This is Taylour-like indeed, when they carry home a Garment, and stolen out cloath, that is kept behind. So you are summing up your discourse, and tell your Reader of a Legal Rite, and keep back the Covenant, the main of all, this is base Theft indeed:) <hi>a far more excellent Testimony of his saving Pleasure concerning Infants, than that was or any legal Rite whatsoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I say, by all which your Reader, if he be not blind, may see, how you labour to delude your silly People with words; pretending to shew your great learning in answering my two unlearned Questions, when as they stand unanswered; and I doubt not but the Seed of a believing <hi>Jew</hi> in Christ may well say, <hi>If this be all we get by our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents believing in Christ come, which this Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptist talks of, give us the old Dispensation again: When we had a God in Covenant to go
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38286:25"/>too, and a Seal of his Covenant to help our Faith; for now we have neither, and so our state is more miserable by Christs coming than it was before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for your Book of your <hi>Anti-Quaeries,</hi> to which you refer me; I will not give so much as a small Needle for it, I have enough of you, by what I read in this.</p>
               <p>As for Bishop <hi>Barlow,</hi> if he be of your Judgment, as you present him, yet I Question whether he be <hi>Dipt:</hi> Ask him I pray, and <hi>bid him not reject the Counsel of God against himself,</hi> as you tell me I do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>I Thought I had done with you, when you had answered my Questions, but it seems no: There are several other faults you find with me, and the first is about <hi>Election in my Sense.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not find the word <hi>Election</hi> mentioned in the <hi>p.</hi> 90. which you direct me to; how then can you know my Sense of it? nor do you tell me what is your Sense; this would run us into another controversie, and then my Book would swell into that bigness, which I resolve it shall not.</p>
               <p>Then you tell your Reader, <hi>Whilst his Book
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38286:25"/>may cause many weak Readers to think that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision did, and that Infant Baptism doth great things towards their Salvation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I do not make your Baptism by Dipping to be of that concernment to Salvation, that none shall be saved without it: but a few words to both.</p>
               <p>And first for <hi>Circumcision,</hi> because your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty told me, <hi>God circumcised the Heart of no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and will not have them to be included in the</hi> Seed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>but onely Adult persons; for Infants cannot love God, as it is there set down.</hi> No more can you, thô you be Adult, answer it, <hi>Legally.</hi> But that God did not circumcise the Hearts of any Infants, then, this I do not believe, upon this ground.</p>
               <p>I cannot conceive, how it can consist with the Wisdom, Holiness, and Goodness of God, to Institute an Ordinance in his Church, for Spiritual and Saving Ends, and strictly to command this Ordinance to be administred to such subjects (as Children of eight dayes old) which are not capable to understand the ordinance, nor Co-work with God in the ordinance; and he himself not to work with his own Institution, when and where he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, to the good and benefit of that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to whom it is Administred, this Subject having need of the Spiritual good Signified and Sealed thereby. It doth implicitely charge the Institution with <hi>Vanity:</hi> And I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38286:26"/>am confirmed the more in it, because all the godly mentioned in the old Testament, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Manasseh,</hi> were such as from their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood grew up in the service of God; so that I Question not, while man did circumcise the <hi>Flesh,</hi> God did circumcise the <hi>Heart.</hi> I gave you an instance of a Child that died before it was five years old, that did express this love to God. Your reason hath thus much strength in it, Because Infants express not the Acts of <hi>Rational</hi> Love, therefore they have not the principle of Rational Love in them.</p>
               <p>The same I may say for Baptism, being Christs own Institution, this in the hand of his Spirit accompanying it, when and where he pleaseth, shall be the mean to convey spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual blessings to the Hearts of some Infants, and prove to them the true <hi>washing of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation;</hi> which I ground upon, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. Where <hi>Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> twice, are given to Baptism as an Instrument in the Hand of the Spirit. How he doth it, I do not trouble my self to answer, I leave that to him that Institutes: If you can tell me how the water of <hi>Jordan</hi> cleansed <hi>Naamans</hi> Leprosie, then possibly I may tell you. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I do not now trouble my self about the signification, meerly because I aim at brevity. How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten do we meet with Christians educated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38286:26"/>godly Parents, troubled, because they could not tell the <hi>Time,</hi> when God first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to work upon them; it hath proved to them a great objection against the soundness of their Work. But if God did begin his Work in their Baptism, and Parents follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God by Prayer, for the blessing of his Ordinance, and remembrance of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, how could they know it, by reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon themselves?</p>
               <p>As for that <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. Whether Baptism be meant by the <hi>Water</hi> there, is a Question very much controverted; I marvel to read <hi>Justin Martyr, Irenaeus, Origen,</hi> &amp;c. All that lived next the Apostles, yea <hi>Totus chorus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitatis,</hi> as <hi>Marlorate</hi> saith, understanding <hi>Baptism</hi> by it, and yet all to be mistaken, our first Annotatours upon the Bible seem to speak well upon it: This I am satisfied in, that the common answer given to it, that it is but of the import with <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost and Fire,</hi> is no answer to it. For God did never institute <hi>Fire,</hi> as he hath done <hi>Water</hi> to be an Element to constitute a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. But of all men the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> that put Salvation in <hi>Dipping,</hi> (whence that silly woman, who told a Friend of mine, <hi>Had I died before I had been baptized</hi> (by <hi>Dipping</hi> she meant) <hi>I had perished;</hi>) they had need un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it so; then tho' Faith come by <hi>Hearing</hi> ordinarily, (I hope all born <hi>deaf</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:38286:27"/>shall not therefore be damned because they cannot hear, and so not believe) yet God hath not so tied up himself to <hi>one</hi> Instrument to work Grace by, because a Carpenter is tied to his Axe if he will hew his Timber.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>If so, then baptize all Children, yea and Men too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> I deny the consequence. For Baptism is a Priviledge belonging to the Church, whereof the Children of visible Believers (being <hi>Saints,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.) are Members with their Parents; and therefore have a right to this initiating Ordinance, which Children out of the visible Church have not.</p>
               <p>Next you fall upon me for the Experience I have found of the benefit of the improving <hi>Abrahams</hi> and my Baptismal-Covenant (which I never thought the World should know, nor ever should have known it, had I not contrary to my own thoughts been drawn forth to appear publickly in this controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,) your Sentence upon it is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It would make a well man sick to see what work he makes of it, for after all his shifting from Post to Pillar, he only gets stomack to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Counsel of God against himself,</hi> Luke 7.30.</p>
               <p>For my rejecting the Counsel of God, the Holy God shall judge between you and me; and for what you scoffe at, I leave it to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38286:27"/>learned, sound, and holy men to judge. But did all Children under <hi>Abraham,</hi> and their Baptismal-Covenant, improve them, and feel the advantage they have by them, in the time of their fears from sin, they would slight all the Anabaptists Books against In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptism as much as I do; and they might sell their Books to the <hi>Tobacco</hi> Shops for other uses.</p>
               <p>Come on then, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> I will take your Sentence into pieces, and consider your words, <hi>Sickness, Post,</hi> and <hi>Pillar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> is Sick, how shall we get him Cured? After some years Study of Physick, I have been a Practitioner of it thirty years, and tho' I have not attained the skill in it some men have, yet if you dare trust your self with me, I will assure you I will do you no harm, if I cannot do you good. But what is your disease, Mr. <hi>Grantham?</hi> I search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your writing to find it out; and at first I thought the signs did not agree; for in one place, <hi>p.</hi> 11. you write thus: <hi>Infants, have no Iniquities for God to Remember, but only Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin to Pardon;</hi> and in several places you tell us, <hi>Infants are Innocent;</hi> now he must be a more cunning Taylour than I am, who can stitch these two words, <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> together. I never knew Innocency need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed pardon before; that <hi>Adam</hi> needed it before his Fall while he was Innocent, is a New
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38286:28"/>Notion to me; but notwithstanding you would have us think you acknowledge Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin, that Infants are guilty of, yet this is only <hi>Peccatum Originans,</hi> by <hi>Imputation,</hi> but for that which is <hi>Peccatum Originatum</hi> (as Divines do distinguish) the inherent Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our fallen Nature; this you plainly deny, by telling us they are Innocent, and corrupting that Text, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And were by Nature the Children of wrath,</hi> most grosly and absurdly; so that I find your disease ly in your head, and you are very sick of the Disease called <hi>Pelagianism.</hi> A proud disease, to lift up sinful man, and debase the Grace of God; for you tell us that Text, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.3. p. 30. <hi>Is best Interpreted of the Adult,</hi> and quoting the verses before, with some variation from the Text too, which ought not to be in Quotations, then you adde, <hi>and so were by Nature Children of Wrath.</hi> I have not yet met with a man <hi>so</hi> audacious to put a word into a Text, which quite varies the sense of the Text; yea and makes the Text speak absurdly. This is sure, they cannot be Children of Wrath by Nature, who are not Children of Sin against God by Nature; Sin onely causeth Wrath: But I pray tell us, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> what is <hi>Nature?</hi> I thought <hi>Natura</hi> had been a <hi>Nascor, Natus.</hi> Which is first I pray, <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Walking,</hi> and <hi>Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> which the verses before speak of? Can
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38286:28"/>any Creature move from place to place, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it be first an <hi>Animal,</hi> hath not an Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal a Locomotive Nature or Principle, and so this <hi>nature</hi> be the cause of the walking? The Child in the Lap hath a locomotive facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tho' as yet it cannot walk, it hath the <hi>nature;</hi> and so the corrupt nature is the cause of its walking Corruptly: this is excellent Logick, the effect to be before the cause. If you consult learned Men, they tell you, That Nature, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the word in the Text, <hi>Primo fignificat generationem ipsam, seu nativitatem.</hi> Ephes. 2.3. <hi>Secundo ipsam rei essentiam.</hi> Gal. 4.8. <hi>Tertio significat proprietatis rei essentiales.</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4.</p>
               <p>This is your Diseale Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> and I will give you a Receipt for the Cure of it, infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible I warrant you.</p>
               <p>R. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Adam begat a Son in</hi> his own <hi>Likeness, after</hi> his <hi>Image:</hi> The Hebrew words for <hi>Likeness,</hi> and <hi>Image,</hi> are both the same in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26, 27. <hi>God Created Man in</hi> his own <hi>Image,</hi> &amp;c. These words, <hi>His own,</hi> in these two Texts are quite opposite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. No need of Circumcising <hi>Isa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acs</hi> Flesh at <hi>eight</hi> days old, if his Heart needed no Curcumcising at the same time. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.16. &amp; Ch. 30. <hi>v.</hi> 6. Add to these <hi>Job</hi> 14.4. <hi>Job.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Job</hi> 25.4. <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. This is Divine Authority, Mr. <hi>Grantham.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:38286:29"/>
               <p>As for humane Authority, <hi>Grotius</hi> on <hi>Luke</hi> 2.22. names several of the Learned <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and their sayings, which shew they were not ignorant of the Corrupt <hi>nature</hi> of Man; other learned Men, quote many places out of <hi>Plato,</hi> where he speaks the same thing. So <hi>Stobeus,</hi> yea <hi>Aristotle,</hi> tho' a great Friend to corrupt nature, yet acknowledge, <hi>there is in us somewhat</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally repugnant to right Reason.</hi> As for the <hi>Romans,</hi> there are <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> who speak so clearly of it, that I can but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at that Judgment of God, in giving up Christians now, to such Blindness, that they cannot see that Evil which the Heathen who had onely the Light of nature, could see, and leave their Testimony against it; yet these men did not know that Original Sin by <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> which is all you acknowledge.</p>
               <p>One word more, Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> and so I will leave you as to this point; you have been a great Professor so long, a Teacher, a great Writer: I doe but ask you, Were you never sensible of, humbled, and abased un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the sense of this corrupt Nature? Then God keep me from the Conversion of those men, who never were so convinced of their vile nature, as to abhor and loath themselves before God, under the Sense of it: as also from them, who are the chief cause of their own Conversion.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38286:29"/>
               <p>I know well, you will allow Gods <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Help</hi> some room in Conversion: but there must be something of our <hi>own</hi> above that, else no Conversion, this Similitude will shew it clearly. After the House of Commons have been a long time consulting about a Bill, read it over three times; sent it to the House of Lords, they have done so too, both Houses met in the <hi>Painted Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and agreed; yet here is no <hi>Law,</hi> it must now be carried to the King, and if he saith, <hi>Le Roy le Veut,</hi> now it is a Law, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth power with it, before it had no power; by this we see where the Supream Power lieth. Thus let the great God set himself to convert a Sinner, use all his moral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from Himself, Promises, Threats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet if it doth not please the Imperial High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Will, to declare and give her Consent, all Gods Actings come to nothing; if it doth, then Conversion is wrought. Let God heal the understanding of its Blindness, (which is done by a Physical act) and now lay Divine objects before it clearly, that it seeth them as they <hi>are, God, Christ, Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> in their adequate goodness, Sin in its evil, and now work so sweetly and rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, affecting the <hi>Will</hi> also by his gracious Presence with it, that now <hi>Sensu Composito,</hi> there is a consequential Necessity for the <hi>Will</hi> to follow the Judgment, else it were Brutish;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38286:30"/>to talk of any kind of necessity, it is such an affront offered to the Perogative, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable breach of the Priviledges of the <hi>Will,</hi> that there must be a Liberty left to her, to admit, or reject all Gods workings, else our ears are filled with out-cries. The way of working I speak of, gives too much Honour to Grace; and that God doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest Grace to one man more than to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and consequently it would argue an Individual personal Election. Hence these men deny Regeneration to Infants, because the Honour of their great <hi>Diana,</hi> the Liberty of the <hi>Will,</hi> would be Eclipsed; for their <hi>Wills</hi> are not thought to act in their Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We shall hear you speak plain anon.</p>
               <p>Now for the <hi>Post,</hi> which is that, Mr. <hi>Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham?</hi> you name this first, and it stands first in my Book, <hi>Gods Covenant with my Father Abraham;</hi> tho' you scoff at it, yet you spake very true, it is a <hi>Post</hi> indeed, not an <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Reed,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21. <hi>on which if a man lean, it will goe into his hand.</hi> No, Mr. <hi>Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> I will venture still to trust and lean upon it, a very strong <hi>Post</hi> to lean on, when a Man is weak.</p>
               <p>Which is the <hi>Pillar?</hi> The next is my Baptismal Covenant, of which the <hi>Post</hi> was the ground: then this <hi>Post</hi> and <hi>Pillar,</hi> in which the <hi>Grace, Goodnesse, Faithfulnesse</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of God are engaged; the Blood and Spirit
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38286:30"/>of Jesus, signified and Sealed unto my Faith embracing both, shall be to me as <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> the two Pillars in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Porch, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 7.21. to help bear up my infirm weak Soul in times of Temptation, for to them I hold. Now, mock on Mr. <hi>Grantham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of your Tribe, a young confident A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptist, tells me, <hi>If you have nothing more to shew for your Covenant Interest in God, as being your God, than that,</hi> (he referrs to that experience I declare in my short Treatise, which made Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> Sick;) <hi>it would be no better than a Lie in your right hand: but I have better hopes of you.</hi> What are the sure Notes of our interest in God, I shall not come to you to learn; but I look upon those notes as good as your <hi>Self-Regeneration</hi> and Better.</p>
               <p>Next he falls upon me <hi>for being asleep when I was Sprinkled and Crossed,</hi> and desires to know of me, <hi>what ground any man hath, his Parents or himself, to</hi> Baptize <hi>any person when they are asleep? this is no idle enquiry, but calls for the Consideration of all serious Christians.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Grantham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You forgot your self, will you allow us to <hi>Baptize,</hi> I was Sprinkled, you tell me: but was I <hi>asleep?</hi> Why would not you wake me? Say, <hi>I was not born then.</hi> Your excuse is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, but how doe you know I was asleep then? I presume so; but remember your Book,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38286:31"/>
                  <hi>Presumption is no proof:</hi> and sure I am all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not asleep when they are brought to be Baptized. The last Child I Baptized was awake, so might I be.</p>
               <p>Baptism, is in the Application of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and <hi>its odds</hi> (to use your words) but the Water did wake me, if I were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleep. If <hi>Isaac</hi> were asleep when he was brought to be Circumcised, <hi>its odds,</hi> but the cutting of his Fore-skin did wake him; but suppose he had not, was it therefore no Circumcision, did it take away the efficacy of the Ordinance? This is a profound Question, where shall we have a place to dispute, and determine it? The Theatre at <hi>Oxford,</hi> is not worthy of such a question; it shall be <hi>Merchant-Taylours</hi> Hall in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then you fall upon me, about <hi>falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not remember any word I had about it. But this shortly I say, If it be true what <hi>yours</hi> prate about here, that a <hi>Person truely regenerate may fall away totally and finally;</hi> I would never preach Comfort to any regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Person, till I see him Dying, and sure he could not live; now I see he hath perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the end, now I will preach Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: So that all the Exhortations of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians to <hi>Rejoyce, Phil.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.16. &amp;c. all the Consolations of the Gospel, may be laid by, for they all depend upon my <hi>Will.</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:38286:31"/>Suppose I have walked fifty years with God, and have but one month to live, whatsoere temptation to sin may befall me in that month, I cannot tell; and what my <hi>Will</hi> may do I cannot tell; <hi>Grace with Mutability</hi> would not keep me in my <hi>Innocent</hi> estate, then <hi>Grace, Mutability,</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> will not keep me in <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> estate; take away <hi>Mutability</hi> out of the first Covenant, <hi>fix</hi> the Will, there will be no need of a second Covenant; and if this Covenant doth not provide some help against Mutability, we are but miserable under it. Alas, what tormenting fears do many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians live under for fear of Non-perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, notwithstanding all the Promises of the Gospel for their support!</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Damning of Infants,</hi> you cry out upon, <hi>and ashamed you are, you say, that the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>and</hi> Independents <hi>should be of that opinion,</hi> for others it seems 'tis no matter.</p>
               <p>I have read <hi>eight</hi> Opinions about the state of Infants after death, Baptized and Unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, but I have not spoken one Word about them: I leave secret things to God.</p>
               <p>Then you are <hi>ashamed of my Conceit,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> Fancy, about <hi>the Soul being Passive in Regeneration.</hi> I shall let it alone to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place: How do you look when you are ashamed, Mr. <hi>Grantham?</hi> do you <hi>Blush?</hi> If you make me one of the Adulterous Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that will not believe without a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38286:32"/>as you speak, yet I will not be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to say, <hi>Regeneration is a Miracle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some</hi> indeed <hi>do abuse,</hi> Ephes. 1.19, 20. <hi>to uphold this false Opinion, that none can believe without such a power as by which Christ was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from the dead; whereas the Apostle</hi> onely <hi>shews that the Faith of Christians doubts not at all, but that the same God which had power to raise up Christ from the dead, has power to raise us up also; this Power is irresistible that raised Christ from the dead, Men and Devils cannot resist it. But the Power of Gods Grace by which God works in men in an ordinary way is not irresistible,</hi> Act. 7.51.</p>
               <p>Indeed and indeed <hi>you</hi> abuse the Text in restraining the sence to the Resurrection of our bodies <hi>onely,</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> puts himself in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Considering himself as a Believer in Christ, but <hi>Paul</hi> was a Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see, and the Pharisees did believe the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.6, 8. So that <hi>Paul</hi> did believe your Interpretation, before he was a Believer in Christ; but to make him a true Believer, yea to make <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> to believe in a crucified Christ sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, to raise us up from the Death of Sin, to the Life of Holiness, it will require as great a power, as that power which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Christ from the Dead. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. speaks the sence clearly. For the resistance spoken of, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. A man hath many Children,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38286:32"/>he commands them things just and good, he exhorts them to obey him, he promiseth, he threatens, he corrects, still they resist him, and will not obey; thus did God with these Children, and they resist; what then, what do you infer hence? <hi>Tho' God</hi> intends <hi>the Conversion of a Soul, and works to attain his End, yet mans will may so Resist him, that God shall fail of the end he intended:</hi> This must be the thing you would maintain, else the Text will not serve your opinion; but God saith, <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.13. <hi>I will work, and who shall let it?</hi> who? any mans <hi>Will:</hi> Take you him, Mr. <hi>Grautham</hi> for your God, whose will you can so resist as to make him fail of his end, when he <hi>Wills and Intends</hi> a gracious work upon the Soul; and by this Resistance of yours, Demonstrate (to use your own word) that <hi>God is not most Blessed:</hi> to fail of ones <hi>Will and Intention</hi> is the want of a degree of Blessedness: my Will is Crost, I cannot have my Will. I will say with profound <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardin
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>De causa Dei,</hi> l. 3. C. 29.</note>, Illum nolo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will not have him for my God, who cannot most omnipotently make me both to Will, and do, what he Wills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The following <hi>Paragraph</hi> speaks strangely; <hi>This strange Doctrine of damning the greatest part of the World, and that before the World was, is so pernicious, that it makes God the Author of all Sin;</hi> and more such stuff, that I care not for tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing it.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:38286:33"/>
               <p>What did you find in my Book, that you write at this rate? you run into other Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, that have no ground for them in my Book.</p>
               <p>I shall not concern my self to give you any Answer: Only thus,</p>
               <p>I know none that say, that God made Men to <hi>Damn them;</hi> that Damnation was the <hi>End</hi> wherefore he made them.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>greater part of the World being Damned,</hi> this offends you: I pray whose Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion are you of? <hi>Huberus? The Promiscuous Salvation of All:</hi> Or are you of <hi>Caelius Secundus Curio</hi>'s Opinion, <hi>That the number of the Elect and Saved, is much greater than the number of the Reprobate and Damned?</hi> whether you, or these, or Christ be truest (<hi>Math.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Few find it;</hi>) the Day of Judgment will determine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>NOw for a few words about <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> which about ten or eleven times you mention in your four leaves against me: <hi>Twice</hi> you tell me, I Sprinkle Children; and I tell you <hi>Once,</hi> it is very false, I never Sprinkle any: If you prove it; <hi>either you Sprinkle or Dip; but you do not Dip,</hi> Ergo, <hi>you Sprinkle:</hi> I deny your Disjunction, so your Syllogism is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38286:33"/>false: <hi>Datur Tertium;</hi> there is a third: I do alwayes in my Administraction, pour such a quantity of Water as may clearly hold forth <hi>Washing,</hi> which is the largest signification of the worp <hi>Baptize;</hi> we Wash by <hi>Dipping,</hi> and we Wash by <hi>Fowring</hi> of Water. When you Baptize your Tables, <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.4. do you car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them to your Ponds or Rivers, and there dowze them under Water? I never saw that Practice yet; but to Baptize them, by Powring Water on them, is common: So did <hi>Elijah</hi> Baptize his Hands, when <hi>Elisha</hi> Powred Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.38. with 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.11. Had the meaning of <hi>Baptize</hi> been only to Plunge under Water, the Spirit would not have directed his Pen-men to use the word to <hi>Tables,</hi> (or <hi>Beds,) Hands, Vessels,</hi> which I see often cleansed without Plunging under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The <hi>Greeks</hi> are no so scanty for words that signifie Washing, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which word the Pen-man used <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet in the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>v.</hi> he uses <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is not so nice as you are. Hence <hi>Castalio,</hi> a Learned Critick, whom <hi>Arminius</hi> did much Honour, therefore you have cause to honour him; he on <hi>Math.</hi> 3.13. saith, <hi>Beza</hi> rejects the words <hi>Baptizo,</hi> and <hi>Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> used by holy Writers, and useth <hi>Lavo,</hi> and <hi>Lotio,</hi> Washing; for which he blames him; not because <hi>Beza</hi> denies the word <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizo</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:38286:34"/>to signifie <hi>Washing,</hi> but because he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from other Writers in that place. Thus we read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Baptisms:</hi> Dipping was but one kind of <hi>Baptism;</hi> there were divers others, but still they were <hi>Baptisms.</hi> We have then Divine Authority for our signification of the Word.</p>
               <p>Nor do I see how that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. which your admired <hi>Plagiary,</hi> Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> makes so much of, serves his turn for <hi>Dipping.</hi> Two things we are sure of from Scripture: 1. <hi>They walked through the Sea upon dry ground;</hi> this is four times recorded: Is the ground dry when you <hi>Dip?</hi> 2. It is said, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.8. <hi>The Floods stood upright as an heap, the Depths were Congealed,</hi> (like Ice;) whence, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.22. it is said, <hi>The Waters were as a Wall unto them,</hi> &amp;c. Then the Waters did not touch them: Do you Dip, and the Waters not touch them whom you Dip? As for the Cloud Powring down Water, that agrees with our <hi>Baptizing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One Question, I Pray; Were there no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren passed thorough the Sea at this time? Yes, no question, thousands; then Children were now Baptized: Were they then Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with their Parents unto <hi>Moses,</hi> and shall they not now unto Christ? Baptized they were; that's the Question.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But you tell me in your Preface, how Christ
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38286:34"/>was Baptized by Dipping;</hi> and so others.</p>
               <p>I Pray tell me, for I profess seriously, I could not tell how to Baptize by <hi>Dipping;</hi> for a little Child I could tell, but not an Adult Person: Did they go into the Water, be it half way, or what you please, and then the <hi>Baptist</hi> dipt the other part? I would never thus be Baptized my self, nor would I so Baptize. When you <hi>Bury,</hi> do your Dead co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themselves half way, and then you cover the rest? If I were to Baptize, being the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrator, I must take the Person, and Plunge him wholly my self under Water, but then I must leave him at the bottom, for my strength could not take him up.</p>
               <p>Again, Though I know we may Bury a Man in his Cloaths, are you sure they Dipt them all in their Cloaths? these things are material to know: Because we know that in <hi>Chysostom</hi>'s time, as <hi>Vossius</hi> tells us, upon a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult that rose about him, Women that were to be Baptized ran away Naked; (your young Rustick Anabaptist tells me, <hi>What if</hi> Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom <hi>tells a lying Story?</hi> though it were <hi>Vossius</hi> tells it, but you may judge the Man by his Language,) so that they then Baptized <hi>Men, Women</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> Naked; (something be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Shame we conceive.) The Lord would not allow the Priest to go up by Steps
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38286:35"/>to his Altar, <hi>That thy Nakedness be discovered thereon,</hi> Exod. 20.26.</p>
               <p>I hear you now Baptize your Females when it is duskish; but why so? Baptism is a holy Institution,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>I hope they have no Garment</hi> appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>to Dipping; bad</hi> John <hi>so? then a Surplice may as well,</hi> &amp;c.</note> fit to be celebrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Noon-time; why do you not <hi>then</hi> Baptize your Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the Younkers stand and look on? how comely this will be! they must also be some time under the Water, that the Water may soak through their Cloaths.</p>
               <p>Yet as to this manner of Baptizing; had the Lord Commanded Baptism to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by plunging the whole Body under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in a Countrey cold, and where it was not the Custom of the People to wash themselves, (unless some Boys and young Fellows in the heat of Summer, as in our Country, I never heard of one Woman that did wash her self in this manner in our Nation) then there had been more reason to urge this manner of Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing; but for the Lord to Institute it first in a hot Countrey, where this dowzing under Water had been in practice a thourand years before his Institution, so that now it was onely his pleasme to make it his Institution, that this plunging under water which hath been in practice so long, shall be done <hi>in my Name,</hi> &amp;c. the Water having this signification, by my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38286:35"/>Authority, this alters the Case very much: This washing among them, being, partly for <hi>Pleasure,</hi> for <hi>Coolness,</hi> for <hi>Health,</hi> and fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent for <hi>Legal Impurities.</hi> I read in <hi>Levit.</hi> 15. three or four Cases in which those Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things or Washings were commanded at all times; and the <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, the whole Body must be baptized, if but a finger were above water it was not rightly performed, (which it seems one of your Baptists observed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving failed in his Act, tells the man he must be Dipt again, as one that stood by relates; I had it from a Friend who knew the mau a zealous Professor before his dipping, but after it fell into gross Vices, and so died;) had the Lord given those Commands in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> many men and women must have lost their Lives, in an ordinary way.</p>
               <p>Hence though we read twice of being bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in Baptism, yet I deny that therefore we are always bound to Baptize by Dipping; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that Mode in that Country was Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed many hundred Years before the Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, so that they did but keep their former Practice, it was nothing to them. But the word signifying <hi>Washing,</hi> as we have Divine Authority for it, which is done as well by <hi>Powring</hi> as by <hi>Plunging;</hi> and we read so often of the Powring of the Spirit, and of Wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Spirit and Blood of Jesus, Washing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38286:36"/>of Regeneration, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Isa.</hi> 32.15. <hi>Isa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. (the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> Translation,) <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26, 27. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. He that obtains these Washings, is as well as he that hath the same Blessings by <hi>Dippings.</hi> That Text Mr. <hi>Petto</hi> quoteth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is very considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Besides what is commonly said, the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of the three thousand in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved to be by <hi>Dipping:</hi> these thoughts I have. When there have been a multitude to be Baptized, the Text have told us where they were Baptized, as <hi>Jordan</hi> Water, <hi>Aenon</hi> Water; so in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> if there were such deep Waters to dip so many thousands, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts was it? The People holding <hi>John</hi> for a Prophet, and there being such Rivers in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> why do we not read that <hi>John</hi> Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <hi>there,</hi> as well as at <hi>Jordan</hi> and <hi>Aenon?</hi> We read of a contemptible Brook or River, <hi>Isa.</hi> 8.6. about <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> a Brook <hi>Kidron,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. After <hi>John</hi> and the Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given to the Apostles, we do not read of any Baptizing in the Scripture which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly prove it was by <hi>Dipping;</hi> No, not the <hi>Eunuch;</hi> the going down to a Spring of Water, does not prove his being dowz'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water. And for the Baptizings in Hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, so often mentioned, that there should be so much Water in their Houses, is unlikely:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38286:36"/>And the Apostles to take up lusty Men in their Arms, and Plunge them in those Waters, is more than my Strength could do, and more than any can prove they did. The Jaylour, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. an ordinary Person in a City, to have so much Water in his House, is unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; we should not find so much Water in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Mens Houses in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Against this 'tis Objected, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.34. saith, <hi>The Jaylour brought them into his House after Baptism,</hi> v. 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. But the Text mentions nothing of their going out of the House, to any other place to be Baptized, that time in the night.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there used, signifies, to <hi>Cause to Ascend;</hi> and so is used, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.39. and in other places: The <hi>Syriac</hi> word in the Text signifies the same, being the same word with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Hebrew, which is used, <hi>Psal.</hi> 139.8. <hi>If I ascend into Heaven:</hi> So the <hi>Arabick</hi> word in the Text, which the Lexicon translates, <hi>Ascendit per Scalas,</hi> to As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend by a Ladder or Stairs: So that the word may refer to his bringing of them up out of the Dungeon, where he had put them for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</p>
               <p>For my part, I am of their opinion, whom I see to be the most Learned and pious, that the Apostles were Indifferent in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38286:37"/>manner of Administration, whether by Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping under water, to hold forth the Bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Christ, (so am I willing to Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster it, if Parents will,) or by Pouring on of water, to signifie the Washing of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and pouring of the Spirit, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and Washing with the Blood of Christ: That Blood which cleanseth from all Sin, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. Onely let me adde this, as we pour upon the <hi>Face</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by which persons are known, so we can pour it all over the Cloaths, which doth more resemble the manner of Burial through the whole world, for ought I know, than the other: When we bury men, we do not use to run them into the Earth, but first dig the Grave, then powr Earth upon them. But for men to be so het upon a Mode of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration, when the word signifies but <hi>Washing,</hi> whether it be by Pouring or Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, it is but a kind or degree of <hi>Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not baptizing this way or that way, but our improving of the Ordinance; and the Spirits accompanying the Ordinance, which must do us good. God hath blessed the Ordinance, when administred by <hi>pouring</hi> on of water. A Gentlewoman (whom I name not) when the <hi>wretched</hi> Doctrine, (as that man of God Mr. <hi>Thomas Hooker</hi> calls it) of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38286:37"/>
                  <hi>Anabaptism</hi> first came up in <hi>England,</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: <hi>Is this</hi> (said she) <hi>the Doctrine now coming up? The greatest Comfort that ever I had from God was from my Infant Baptism:</hi> A Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman so eminent in Holiness, that few that are <hi>dipt</hi> must come near her. One of yours told me it is no Baptism: but we shall not go to Anabaptists, to learn any thing that belongs to God. Water is <hi>essential</hi> to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, not Dipping. Dip a man over head and ears in Milk or Wine in the <hi>Name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c. here is no Baptism: pour Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the Person, in the <hi>Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. here is Baptism. This signifies something.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>I Have a little Reckoning with one of your Disciples, who makes a great noise about us; brought up to the Plough, but being of good natural parts, hath devoted himself so to the reading your, and other Books, that he never laboured more in sowing his <hi>Wheat,</hi> than he hath in sowing this <hi>Darnell. Infant-Baptism,</hi> he tells us, is an <hi>Antichristian Cheat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Help us I pray in this juncture of time,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38286:38"/>tell us, who is this <hi>Antichrist?</hi> What kind of Creature is he? where dwells he? There is a great pudder about him; some say he is come: others say he is not come. You tell me of your <hi>Judgment,</hi> in your scribling; I pray give me your <hi>Judgment</hi> here. If you say he is come, when was the time he Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared? None of all the Authors, that I have read, and I have read divers upon that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, say that he was come so long as the Ten Persecutions lasted; no, nor so long as the Emperour kept his Seat in <hi>Rome.</hi> But we find Infant-Baptism practised above a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before the ten Persecutions ended; nor was Infant-Baptism the least advantage to his rising. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> lived near the Apostles time, and then it was in practice: he tells us Christ was an Infant, and <hi>sanctified In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. Origen</hi> was born about 186. and in the year 203. when his Father <hi>Leonides</hi> suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Martyrdom under <hi>Severus;</hi> he wrote to his Father, and encouraged him to suffer it chearfully. He was then about Seventeen years of Age; and he writes, that the Church recived the Baptism of Infants from the Apostles. How then can this be an <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Cheat,</hi> when Antichrist was not come above a hundred years after it was in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, as we read in them, and they write they had it from the Apostles? <hi>Cyrpian</hi> was
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38286:38"/>Martyred under the Eighth Persecution; if you can read his Epistle to <hi>Fidus,</hi> you may then see whether <hi>Infant-Baptism</hi> was not in practice. By this you declare your self to be a Cheater.</p>
               <p>You tell me, <hi>Your way of application of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the body</hi> (in Baptism) <hi>is a fine flesh-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. What do you mean by <hi>Flesh? Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Flesh?</hi> O what a high degree of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of the Flesh is this, for a person to be Dipt! Is that the reason that Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists are such mortified Pervons above others? If it had been so, it had been the better for some of my Relations, which is one reason why I shall not be in love with Anabaptism in haste.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do you mean <hi>Natural Flesh?</hi> We read in the Scripture, so soon as any were made Believers in Christ, they were presently Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; why do not you so soon as you have made a Proselyte, presently Dip him, or her, tho' it be a hard Frost and Snow? will you not stay till the season be warmer? and is not this a little pleasing to the <hi>Flesh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could not tell upon what Scripture ground these Anabaptists denied Communion with all Churches but themselves. I instanced in some, that I am sure there are none such amongst the Anabaptists, nor hath the Sun shined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38286:39"/>better since the Apostles daies: the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion was not, Why not communion with me? But your Answer which you learned from your Masters, is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are</hi> Rantized, <hi>not</hi> Baptized, <hi>and such you admit to your Communion, but the Apostle chargeth us,</hi> 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.6. that we withdraw from <hi>every brother that walketh disorderly. This</hi> Rantizing <hi>was brought in by</hi> Rome <hi>and the Church of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> What a Grecian are you become on a sudden; <hi>Rantizing, Rantiz'd, Rantism,</hi> I read in your Letters. Decline <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For my self <hi>first;</hi> how do you know I was <hi>Rantized?</hi> did you see it? It was forty years before you were born, if it were so. For others; how do you know they were <hi>Rantized?</hi> All your ground is from the Common-Prayer Book. But what if there be no such word as <hi>Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> or <hi>Rantizing</hi> in the Administration of Baptism? You that can charge the Ancient Fathers with <hi>Ignorance,</hi> (as we shall hear anon) and <hi>Chrysostom</hi> with <hi>Lying,</hi> you should speak and write nothing but <hi>Truth;</hi> but there is no such word: for in both Editious the words are these; <hi>The Minister naming the Child, shall dip it in the water, so it be discretly and warily done. And if the Child be weak, it shall be sufficient to powr water upon it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where is <hi>Sprinkling?</hi> is powring and sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38286:39"/>the same? <hi>I am ashamed,</hi> saith Mr. <hi>Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> &amp;c. You have cause to be so, and all the Anabaptists, whose mouths are full of a word to reproach us by, when there is no such thing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to your Text, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.6. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism is not so much as mentioned in neither of the Epistles: Now it lies upon your party to prove, that <hi>Paul</hi> left this <hi>Tradition</hi> with the Church, to Baptize no Infants, and to Baptize onely by <hi>Dipping.</hi> Which I am sure all the Anabaptists in the World can never do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To walk <hi>disorderly</hi> here, is not to walk after the <hi>Tradition;</hi> what the Apostle aims at, you may see, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.11. <hi>To work with your own hands, as we commanded you.</hi> Now compare this Tradition with the 11. <hi>vers.</hi> of this <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> which you quote against us, and read their disorderly walking, what it was: <hi>For we hear there are some walk disorderly among you, working not at all:</hi> This was contrary to his Command, and Tradition; this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle condemns from his own practice, <hi>v.</hi> 7. Thus from the 6. <hi>vers.</hi> to the 13<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>v.</hi> the Apostle tells you what he means by <hi>disorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walking,</hi> and this is contrary to the <hi>Light of Nature.</hi> But the Light of Nature teacheth us, in <hi>all</hi> Religions, the Children are reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Parents.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:38286:40"/>
               <p>For other sins, the Apostle hath given us directions what to do in other places, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It is well known, those Churches, do maintain the Ordinance of Baptism, use it reverently, teach the improvement of it; suppose there were some defect in the mode of Administration (here is no <hi>Imposition</hi> upon you, of any thing humane,) is this a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground to unchurch all the Churches in the world but your selves? The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire this at your hands.</p>
               <p>When I framed this Argument from <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. which was urged against <hi>Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Children must not be baptized because they cannot believe, then neither can they be saved because they do not believe. Both <hi>Baptism</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> depend upon one and the same <hi>Condition,</hi> i. e. <hi>Believing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Grif:</hi> denied the Consequence, telling me that Text speaks onely of Adult persons. So does 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. &amp; 5. Hence two Positions he gave me.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>God regenerates no Infants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>God doth not Circumcise the hearts of any Infants.</hi> By this it seems, no not the heart of <hi>John</hi> Baptist. I have spoken to this before, onely I add to this, Dr. <hi>Homes</hi> conceives
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38286:40"/>that Text <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. to have its fulfilling chiefly, when the <hi>Jews</hi> shall be called. When I observed well the Verses going before, and consider <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. I should not oppose him, then the great Body of the Infant-Seed of the <hi>Jews</hi> shall experience the truth of the Promise, and Anabaptism shall be exploded.</p>
               <p>I asked, If God Regenerates no Children, how shall they be saved? He answered, <hi>All Infants dying such are Justified and Saved.</hi> Rom. 5.18. (To this Text I spake before.)</p>
               <p>The young Scribler was so full with this notion, that thus he writes to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ignorance there was in some you reckon as great Fathers, of the Justification that is by the Blood of Christ for Infants, caused them to invent their</hi> Infant Rantism, <hi>to take away</hi> Original Sin, <hi>and they together with the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>if not some of the Presbyterians, do reckon it a Regenerating Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What stuffe is here! The Reader may judge the spirit of this Anabaptist, how proud, bold, and confident it is; that if he had the Books of these learned, ancient, godly Men laid before him, he could not read one line to understand it, ye the dares charge them with <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>Lies</hi> beside. Could this young
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38286:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:38286:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:38286:42"/>Fellow that charges these ancient Fathers with <hi>Ignorance,</hi> but read <hi>Justin Martyr, Athanasius, Hierom, Epiphanius, Augustin, Ambrose, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nyss. Basil, Macarius,</hi> &amp;c. I would point him to places in their Books, where he should find, they understood, our Justification, I mean of <hi>all</hi> persons before God, to be onely by <hi>Christs Righteousness.</hi> As for <hi>Dipping,</hi> we know it was their practice, thô in some Cases they did allow the Baptizing by Powring of water, (for so the words in <hi>Crypian, Eò quod aqua salutari, non loti sint, sed perfusi.</hi> So <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin.</hi> In those hot Countries, they did ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily use Dipping, we do not deny;) but from the signification of the word, we judge it <hi>Indifferent.</hi> I add but this, thô I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Christs <hi>Burial</hi> to be a part of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, yet our <hi>Redemption, Justification, Reconciliation, Mortification of Sin,</hi> are all given to the <hi>Righteousnesse, Blood, Sacrifice, Crosse</hi> of Christ: <hi>His Death,</hi> before his <hi>Burial. It is finished,</hi> said Christ upon the Cross, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.30. before they <hi>Buried</hi> him.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Original Sin,</hi> indeed they were sound and clear in that Doctrine, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in their Homiles and Articles, are very full and clear, thô you be rotten. What God doth in Baptism, we leave to his Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>But at this rate doth his Pen run in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38286:42"/>to me. And this is the Spirit of the Arminian-Anabaptists in other places; as I know the Town, where the Minister gave them a Meeting to discourse them. One that was an Auditor told me, the worst term the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister used was <hi>Friend,</hi> but <hi>their</hi> Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him very unworthy. As to his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> they might have spared him. For he did no more than Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> the <hi>Antesigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> of all Anabaptists, hath written in defence of it. When they urged him for a <hi>positive Command</hi> for Infant-Baptism; he told them, If we must have a Positive Command for all things we practise, or lay it by, then we must lay by the Observation of the <hi>Lords day:</hi> They yielded this, saying, <hi>All daies were alike with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But since you are so charitable to Insants, how far will you extend your Charity? It must go further than Infants. You tell me, <hi>To preach the Gospel to a Child in the Cradle, were ridiculous: and that they are</hi> Disciples <hi>who hear, learn, and embrace the doctrine they hear.</hi> But Children are not capable of these; hence exclude them from Baptism.</p>
               <p>But doth Scripture own none other for <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples?</hi> Compare <hi>Acts</hi> 15. <hi>vers.</hi> 10. with <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21. the Question was about <hi>Circumcision,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38286:43"/>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 1. In the 10. <hi>v.—to put a yoke upon the neck of the Disciples:</hi> They upon whose necks they would impose Circumcision were <hi>Disciples,</hi> this is clear. Now in <hi>Act.</hi> 21.21. they tell <hi>Paul</hi> what is reported of him, viz. <hi>That he did teach the</hi> Jews, <hi>they ought not to Circumcise their children.</hi> Then Children are Disciples, at eight daies old.</p>
               <p>I desire your wisdom would determine, what years Children must or may be of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to that <hi>capacity,</hi> to understand, learn, and embrace the doctrine they hear, as to an outward appearance.</p>
               <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which signifies a Child, <hi>Paul</hi> useth five times in one verse, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. <hi>He spake,</hi> he <hi>understood,</hi> he <hi>reasoned,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as a Child.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, a Child is so accounted untill he be nine years old and a day: Sure I am, there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Children who before they be capable to understand, learn, and embrace Gospel-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, can rebell against Parents, Curse Swear, speak Filthily, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if these dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> under that <hi>incapacity,</hi> their incapacity it seem makes them to be justified and saved by Christs Righteousness: O Happy Childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who dye in such a State.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:38286:43"/>
               <p>But hold a little, are they all justified, and saved? then it must be by the Covenant of Grace, and shall they be under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant so, as to be in a justified and saved state by it, and not have the Seal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? You may say what you please, but give a solid reason why you yield a Person the Covenant, and deny the Seal; when did you ever know it among men? but this we have gained now, that not only the Infant Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but all Infants in the World have a right to Baptism.</p>
               <p>As for your Texts, by which you prove Infants can have no Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. nor be regenerated, because we are begotten by the Word, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I had prepared several Answers to them, but I saw my book grew too big, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them. I shall give you but your own answer, which you give to <hi>John</hi> 3.3. and 5. and <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. The Texts speak only of <hi>Adult</hi> Persons, but that God can infuse Grace no way into the Heart but by the <hi>ear,</hi> and that he hath tied up himself to one Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this you are to prove. Divers learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Divines, and I believe some of your own party, conceive, that the conversion of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38286:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:38286:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:38286:45"/>
                  <hi>Jews</hi> shall be, not by Hearing, but by Sight, as <hi>Pauls</hi> was; Christ <hi>appearing in the Clouds, Rev.</hi> 1.7. compared with <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. Hence <hi>Isa.</hi> 66.8, 9. <hi>Shall a Nation be born at once?</hi> However, can you tell how that <hi>Wise</hi> one frames the Body of the Child, and infuseth (according to most mens opinions) the Soul into the Body, while it is in the womb? If not that, can you tell what he doth with the Soul? Can he not infuse Grace into the Soul, as the Soul into the Body? which is hardest?</p>
               <p>To prove then Infants may be regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, three or four Arguments I shall use, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side what I spake before of Heart-circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, from <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) If all, even Adult Persons, are <hi>Passive</hi> in the Work of Regeneration, then Infants are capable of Regeneration: But the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is true.</p>
               <p>Some Ladies have their Husbands Pictures drawn at large, these hang up in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; they have them also drawn in a Little compass, and hang them upon their breasts: This Blessed Limner draws his Image upon little Children, as well as upon Adult Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. The <hi>Shunamites</hi> Child lies Dead, 2 <hi>King.</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38286:45"/>4.20. <hi>Lazarus</hi> lies dead, <hi>John</hi> 11.14. <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> tho' Adult doth no more towards his <hi>Quickning,</hi> the receiving of his Soul into Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his Body, than the <hi>Shunamites</hi> Child did, they were equally <hi>Passive;</hi> so are all they who are dead in trespasses and sins, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1, 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>To this you answer, <hi>What you say of the Adult being</hi> Passive <hi>in the work of Regeneration, I know that you and others say so; but from what ground I know not; Is not Hearing and Receiving an Active work? is not Faith and Repentance which are the two parts of Regeneration, Acts of the Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Your false Grammar I let pass, and for brevity sake, let <hi>Hearing</hi> alone. But for Faith and Repentance, the two parts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, are Acts of the Soul; but tell me, whether of a Soul <hi>Dead</hi> or <hi>Quickned?</hi> If Quickned, how comes this Soul to be Quickned, that it might have a Principle or Power to put forth these Acts? Were you <hi>Active</hi> or <hi>Passive</hi> in the work of Quickning? It seems by your Answer you were <hi>Active;</hi> then you were never Dead, or else <hi>Death</hi> is active to <hi>Life, Corruption</hi> to <hi>Grace, Hell</hi> to <hi>Heaven.</hi> Much good may your <hi>Self-Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> do you: So your <hi>Self-Creation;</hi> for so the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38286:46"/>work is called, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.10. and 14. <hi>v.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p>You tell me, <hi>Seminal Faith and Repentance,</hi> which I affirm, <hi>is but the Fiction of mens brains,</hi> and so of my brain; let me try it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They who are regenerated have Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But all Infants saved, are regenerated.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>All Infants saved, have. Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> but these do not show themselves in Act, then it must be but <hi>Seminal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is clear from your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, who tell me, they are the two parts of Regeneration, now where the <hi>whole</hi> is, the <hi>parts</hi> must needs be.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor,</hi> I prove.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They who are born unclean, that are sinful and corrupt by Nature, must be regenerated before they can be saved: But so are all Infants born.</hi> Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is the part to be proved. For this I gave your Master <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> and <hi>Humane Authority,</hi> read the Texts.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:38286:46"/>
               <p>To this you Answer, <hi>Children being Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from</hi> Adams <hi>Sin,</hi> (which is not yet prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>no other Sin they are guilty of,</hi> (say you in another Letter;) <hi>What other Sin have they committed, that should hinder them from coming to Heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How finely you answer! Does my Argument speak of <hi>Committing Sin?</hi> tho' as I have told your Master, Children do that too. I argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from their <hi>Birth Sin;</hi> our Lord laies the necessity of Regeneration, from our <hi>Birth Sin,</hi> Joh. 3.5, 6. <hi>That which is Born of the Flesh is Flesh.</hi> If we are born <hi>Clean, Spiritual, Sinless,</hi> then give all the Texts I have there mentioned the <hi>Lie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to <hi>Seminal Faith, Repentance, and so of all Graces;</hi> if of any Grace, then of Faith and Repentance as well. I thought alwayes, that <hi>Seeds or Roots</hi> had been before <hi>Fruits; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> before <hi>Operations, Habits</hi> before <hi>Acts.</hi> I read indeed of one Act without a Habit, but it was <hi>Miraculous, Numb.</hi> 22.28, 30. <hi>Balaams</hi> Ass <hi>speaks,</hi> and Discourses with <hi>Balaam,</hi> a Rational Act; but it hath no Rational Soul. When God regenerates an Adult Person, he doth first infuse the Principles, Seeds, Habits, of all the Graces of the Spirit, before he can act and bring forth the Fruits of the Spirit:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38286:47"/>When the Sower went out to Sow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.3. it was but the Seed of <hi>Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> which he did sow, and which was first received; and these Seeds grow up, <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.27. It is the <hi>Seed which remains,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Peters</hi> Faith failed fadly as to the Act, but the Seed remained.</p>
               <p>Since then this is but a <hi>Fiction of my brain,</hi> do you Twi-fallow and Tri-fallow your Ground, but Sow no <hi>Seed,</hi> for according to your Doctrine you may have a Crop with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it: If you do cast in Seed, look for the Fruit next day, according to your Doctrine, for if God sow in the Hearts of little Ones the Seeds of all the Graces of his Spirit, they must show themselves presently in Fruits.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Argument.</hi> No unclean Person shall ever see God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p>But Infants by Nature are <hi>born Ʋnclean,</hi> if the Scripture may be believed: they must bear that Image in which they were created by God, that ever see the face of God.</p>
               <p>All the members of the Kingdom of Heaven are <hi>Holy,</hi> but Children are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Kingdom of Heaven: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38286:47"/>Holy, but not by Birth, it is by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.</p>
               <p>The Foundation of <hi>Anabaptism,</hi> lies in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <hi>Original Sin,</hi> as did <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and he was against Baptizing Infants upon this Ground.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) If <hi>Adam</hi> had continued in Innocency, his Children had born the Image of God from the Birth: I never heard it denied, that which I infer hence, is, That Children are capable of the Image of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Seeds of all Grace; it was so <hi>then,</hi> why not now? Shall the Sin of one Person be so mischievous to deprive <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his Posterity of the Image of God, and bring the Seeds of all Corruption into their Nature; and shall the Grace of God be denied to renew his Image in little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when and where he pleaseth? Children being a great part of the World, shall the Spirit of God have nothing to do in their Hearts? <hi>Adams Disobedience</hi> far exceeds the <hi>Obedience</hi> of Christ, which the Apostle compares in Justification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.16, 17, 18. For his <hi>Disobedience</hi> could defile all his Posterity, but Christs <hi>Obedience</hi> doth not cleanse and regenerate <hi>one</hi> Child: Our <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi> is as truely the purchase of Christ
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38286:48"/>as our <hi>Justification.</hi> The Spirit of the second <hi>Adam</hi> repairs that Image in those Subjects which the first <hi>Adam</hi> hath defaced, when and where he pleaseth; but he hath defaced it in Infants, if the Scriptures may be believed, before this kind of <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> which you and your Master are of: I do not think all <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> deny Original Sin, or <hi>Sin of our Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">(4.) If all Children dying such are justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and saved, then there will be Millions in Heaven in whom the Spirit of God, <hi>as the Third Person in the Blessed Trinity,</hi> had nothing to do in their Salvation: That Rule, <hi>Omnes Operationes ad extra,</hi> &amp;c. does not take off my Argument. For the Distinct Subsistences, have their Distinct Manner of Working; and I speak of the Spirit under that Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. The Father <hi>Decrees</hi> Redemption. The Son (assuming our Nature) works out, and laies down the <hi>Price</hi> for our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Spirit <hi>Applies</hi> Redemption. The Consummation of things is given to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: so Regeneration is given to the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5, 8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.13. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. There is Christ for Justification, and Spirit for Sanctification.</p>
               <p>I adde no more, these with what I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before are enough.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:38286:48"/>
               <p>Because you find I am not for <hi>sprinkling,</hi> you hope I may be brought over to be <hi>Dipt,</hi> and tell me, <hi>you should therein greatly rejoice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If you do not rejoyce before, you shall not rejoyce in hast. For, (1.) Were I waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, I know no right Administratour: for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake up your Principles. 1. Baptism is the <hi>Form</hi> of a Church. 2. No Baptism but by Dipping. 3. You grant Pastours must be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alled by the Church, then there must be a Church onely by Dipping to call these Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours; now according to Scripture, these Pastours must be <hi>Able men,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Ordination,</hi> there must be a <hi>Presbytery</hi> (or Bishop over Presbyters, but the Bishop Dipt, I will yield that too,) of Able Men Dipt: Now where were there such Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t first, with such Presbyteries, or Bishop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver Presbyters to call, and ordain, is more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an ever I heard of; and if not such, I know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o right Administratour, and if not so, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alue all your Dipping not worth a Rush.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Thô God overlooks the Infirmities of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s, and I doubt not some are sound in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>her points, and Conscientious, yet to very any, it hath proved a <hi>Blasting</hi> errour. How
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38286:49"/>many have proved Corrupt in Doctrines, and Immoral in their Conversations, who were not so before Dipping. Major <hi>Packer,</hi> thô an Anabapist, yet a sober Man, complained to a worthy Friend of mine: <hi>'Tis our unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, that a man cannot be an Anabaptist, but presently he must be an Arminian.</hi> So it seems by you. And now men have Repentance pinn'd upon their sleeves. A friend of mine discours<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an Anabaptist, asked him, <hi>If you sin can you repent when you list?</hi> Yes, said he. Sin he could be sure, for he could be drunk: for his Repentance, which he found so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, let him look that it be as found. That is very observable which Dr. <hi>Winter</hi> relates, of that Anabaptist, executed for a Capital Crime, who confessed, <hi>That from the time of his going under water, he sensibly found God Departing from him.</hi> I spare to write what Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Doctrine I have heard among them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides these: Out of whose Hive the <hi>Quakers</hi> swarm'd for the greater part, is well known, going from Gospel Light to Natural Light, and further they cannot go.</p>
               <p>That Hypocrites, and Apostates may be found in other Churches, who doubts it? but when men put such a stress upon a Mode of the Administration of an Ordinance, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Salvation depended on it, and keep such a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38286:49"/>stir to make Proselytes, and joy so if they get one, and tell us they must be Regenerate, <hi>Israel</hi> according to the Spirit, Saints by Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they must do the work of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that now are <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, these must be the Baptized ones, and hence exclude all Infants; yet after these, to prove so corrupt in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as very many of them are, and too many vitious in Conversation, I may well call it a <hi>Blasting</hi> Opinion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I shall be wary of that <hi>German</hi> Errour, which made such work there, and would make little better here were the Power in your hands, if all be of the same spirit with those who by Marriage bear some Relation to me; and I am confirmed in it the more from that passage of Mr. <hi>Hutcheson</hi> to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> calling upon him to <hi>Repent of that absurd</hi> and Heretical <hi>Position of a Baptismal Covenant of Grace, running in a Fleshly</hi> ('tis false, for 'tis a Believing) <hi>Line,</hi> &amp;c. If Infant-Baptism be a <hi>Heresie,</hi> let Ministers look to themselves, if Anabaptists get the power.</p>
               <p>To conclude: When Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi>'s book first came out, and made such a noise in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, two other Ministers being with me, we got his Book, laid it upon the Table, but they would not open it, till first we bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38286:50"/>our knees to the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> begging of him that he would please to enlighten us, that we might know his Mind, and if he had revealed his Truth to this Man, that we might see it: Engaging to God, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever had been the Opinion of our Fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or our own Opinion to the contrary; and tho' this Doctrine was a Novelty, odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and would render them contemptible who did practise it, yet if it were his Truth, his Mind and Will, we would yield up our selves and practise it. Prayer being ended, we opened the Book, the first thing we met with was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant, this we liked well. We read him with great Intention of mind, examined every line, and found him fall very short of proving the Repeal of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant; failing here, we laid by his Book, and regard him no more. They persisted in their practice of Infant-Baptism to their Dying daies, and so shall I.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38286:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>